<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-02T15:26:42+01:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/feed.xml</id><title type="html">MattCASmith</title><subtitle>A blog about cyber security and technology</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Network connections and packet crafting on the Linux command line</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2020/08/27/network-connections-packet-crafting-linux-command-line" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Network connections and packet crafting on the Linux command line" /><published>2020-09-02T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-02T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2020/08/27/network-connections-packet-crafting-linux-command-line</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mattcasmith.net/2020/08/27/network-connections-packet-crafting-linux-command-line">&lt;p&gt;The problem with taking leave during a pandemic is that there are very few places you can go that don’t present an unnecessary risk. For me at least, the thought of taking a plane abroad wasn’t appealing, and neither were the Tube journeys that would be necessary to go out and about in London. To save myself from three weeks of &lt;a href=&quot;http://mattcasmith.net/2019/01/25/football-manager-addictive-spreadsheet/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Football Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and repeats of &lt;em&gt;The Office&lt;/em&gt;, I stocked up on cyber security books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally completed my first runthrough of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/CISSP-Certified-Information-Security-Professional/dp/1119475937/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the mammoth CISSP study guide&lt;/a&gt;, brushed up on my PowerShell with &lt;a href=&quot;https://nostarch.com/powershellsysadmins&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;PowerShell for Sysadmins&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and took some time to improve my Wireshark skills with &lt;a href=&quot;https://nostarch.com/packetanalysis3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Practical Packet Analysis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The latter was certainly my favourite - Chris Sanders’ book serves as both a very practical exploration of packet analysis and just about the best introduction to networking fundamentals I’ve come across. It’s certainly one I’ll be recommending to my colleagues when I return to the (virtual) office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I finished &lt;em&gt;Practical Packet Analysis&lt;/em&gt;, I decided I wanted to increase my familiarity not only with Wireshark and analysis techniques, but also how the packets are generated in the first place. It’s easy enough to run &lt;code&gt;ping&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;nslookup&lt;/code&gt; and observe the results, but when it came to manually crafting packets I was only vaguely aware of where to start, and it seemed like a useful area to explore. So I fired up a couple of Linux virtual machines, opened Google, and got searching for tools and tutorials to help me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a brief overview of some of the tools I experimented with. Some of them allow you to create packets, others TCP connections - but all of them are worth spending some time with to send some packets, generate some PCAPs, and learn more about how your network functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;contents&quot;&gt;Contents&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. &lt;a href=&quot;#netcat&quot;&gt;netcat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
2. &lt;a href=&quot;#bash&quot;&gt;Bash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
3. &lt;a href=&quot;#scapy&quot;&gt;Scapy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
4. &lt;a href=&quot;#sendip&quot;&gt;SendIp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;netcat&quot;&gt;netcat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with a classic. A favourite among cyber security professionals, &lt;code&gt;netcat&lt;/code&gt; is a tool that can be used to send and receive data between systems, either via TCP or via UDP with the &lt;code&gt;-u&lt;/code&gt; flag. A listener is set up using the &lt;code&gt;-l&lt;/code&gt; flag - for example, the command below would start a listener on UDP port 372.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lu&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;372&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this system listening for UDP datagrams on port 372, we can now use &lt;code&gt;netcat&lt;/code&gt; to send data from a second system. The command to begin sending data is quite similar to the one for setting up the listener - just this time we remove the &lt;code&gt;-l&lt;/code&gt; flag and specify the IP address we want to transmit the data to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;u&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;192.168&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;234.128&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;372&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any text that is sent over the new connection is displayed almost immediately in the terminal of the receiving machine, which is fine if you’re sitting watching the Linux terminal and waiting for quite a short message, as in the example communication between the two VMs below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/netcat_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of Linux, however, is that we can easily chain together commands to achieve more than they could individually. Let’s say we want to send an image file via &lt;code&gt;netcat&lt;/code&gt;, for example. We can use &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;|&lt;/code&gt; to read the contents of the file on the sending machine and save it on the receiving machine. To receive the image via a TCP connection on port 555, the recipient would use the following command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;l&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;555&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;received_image&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;png&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sender would do almost the exact opposite, piping the contents of the original image file to the &lt;code&gt;netcat&lt;/code&gt; connection in order to transmit it over the network to the recipient’s system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cat&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;image_to_send&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;png&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;192.168&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;234.128&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;555&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;cat&lt;/code&gt; reads the contents of the image file, which are piped to our &lt;code&gt;netcat&lt;/code&gt; connection. The receiving system sends the data received over the connection to its own image file, and when we check the file itself via the GUI we can see that the image data was successfully transmitted and saved to disk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/netcat_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These examples only scratch the surface of what is possible with &lt;code&gt;netcat&lt;/code&gt;, and I’d encourage you to play around with it to see what it is capable of. SANS has &lt;a taget=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.sans.org/security-resources/sec560/netcat_cheat_sheet_v1.pdf&quot;&gt;a particularly handy cheat sheet&lt;/a&gt; with common commands and accepted flags and options to help you get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;Bash&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we’re on the topic of sending messages and files over the network, it’s also worth noting that the Linux Bash terminal actually has a built-in capability for this using &lt;code&gt;/dev/tcp/&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;/dev/udp/&lt;/code&gt;. Simply add an IP address and port and send your data to this directory, and Linux will handle the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Hello. I'm sending this from the Linux terminal.&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dev&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tcp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;192.168&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;234.128&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;824&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example, I’ve used &lt;code&gt;echo&lt;/code&gt; to send a text message over the network, but I could equally have used &lt;code&gt;cat&lt;/code&gt; and a filename to send a file like we did with &lt;code&gt;netcat&lt;/code&gt;. A &lt;code&gt;netcat&lt;/code&gt; listener on the recipient’s system receives the message and outputs it to the terminal as in our first &lt;code&gt;netcat&lt;/code&gt; example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/bash_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you notice the small difference in the output above? When all the data has been received, the TCP connection is closed and the listener stops. If we were expecting to receive more data later, we could use &lt;code&gt;netcat&lt;/code&gt;’s &lt;code&gt;-k&lt;/code&gt; flag, which would keep the listener active. The TCP connection is still closed when the transfer is complete, but the listener persists and allows the creation of additional TCP connections as they are needed in response to connection requests from clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another difference to using &lt;code&gt;netcat&lt;/code&gt; to send data was that we did not need to use &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt; to send data from a TCP port using &lt;code&gt;/dev/tcp/&lt;/code&gt; - useful to know for scenarios where there are restrictions in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scapy&quot;&gt;Scapy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s move down a level and take a look at some tools for manually crafting packets. &lt;a href=&quot;https://scapy.net/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Scapy&lt;/a&gt; is a Python tool that allows you to send custom packets, individually manipulating fields and flags via a series of commands and options to send exactly the data you want - very useful for testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say I want to check &lt;a href=&quot;http://mattcasmith.net/2020/02/15/pi-hole-samsung-smart-tv/&quot;&gt;my Pi-hole DNS server&lt;/a&gt; is functioning correctly and returning responses when it receives queries. I can manually craft a DNS request for my domain, &lt;code&gt;www.mattcasmith.net&lt;/code&gt;, using the following command within Scapy to specify fields like the destination address/port and DNS query.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dst&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;{pihole_ip}&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;UDP&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dport&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;53&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DNS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;qd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DNSQR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;qname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;www.mattcasmith.net&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)),&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;verbose&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I specify the Pi-hole’s IP address and the UDP port 53 (used for DNS) as the destination, and provide the domain to be queried with the &lt;code&gt;qname&lt;/code&gt; parameter. If all goes well, Scapy will send the packet to the DNS server and print the packet it receives in response, as below. If we wanted to review this data in a nicer format, we could also have run Wireshark or &lt;code&gt;tcpdump&lt;/code&gt; at the same time to generate a PCAP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/scapy_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By reviewing the response above, we can see that the Pi-hole has successfully returned a response. Between the &lt;code&gt;DNSRR&lt;/code&gt; tags we can see that the DNS server has returned several IP addresses associated witht the domain, as we’d see in the output of a tool like &lt;code&gt;nslookup&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;dig&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sendip&quot;&gt;SendIp&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another means to the same end is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www-x.antd.nist.gov/ipv6/sendip.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;SendIp&lt;/a&gt; - a Linux command line tool that enables you to craft custom packets in a similar way to Scapy. Rather than sending another DNS query, let’s go back to an earlier example and set up a &lt;code&gt;netcat&lt;/code&gt; listener on UDP port 904 to receive a text message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sendip&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ipv4&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;192.168&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;234.130&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;udp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;us&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;5070&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ud&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;904&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;d&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;This is a datagram sent with sendip from the command line.&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;v&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;192.168&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;234.128&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The length of the SendIp command reflects the additional flexibility we have compared to when we sent a similar message with &lt;code&gt;netcat&lt;/code&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;-p&lt;/code&gt; flag sets our protocols - in this case IPv4 at the network layer and UDP at the transport layer - and after each we specify the contents of various header fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that SendIP allows us to set the IP source address manually with &lt;code&gt;-is&lt;/code&gt; as well as the UDP source port with &lt;code&gt;-us&lt;/code&gt;. In testing scenarios, including penetration tests, this would allow us to spoof packets from different machines, with much greater control over the packet and header contents than with &lt;code&gt;netcat&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the &lt;code&gt;-d&lt;/code&gt; flag declares the contents of the packet payload - in this case the text message, which we can see in the output on the recipient’s system is received by the &lt;code&gt;netcat&lt;/code&gt; listener.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/sendip_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the tools and examples above represent different ways of sending data over a network from the Linux command line. While I used simple text and file exchanges to demonstrate how they work, these tools have many different features and options and can be used in much more complex scenarios. Hopefully this post has given you some idea of how they work and what they are capable of, and given you enough of a starting point to try some experiments of your own.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><summary type="html">The problem with taking leave during a pandemic is that there are very few places you can go that don’t present an unnecessary risk. For me at least, the thought of taking a plane abroad wasn’t appealing, and neither were the Tube journeys that would be necessary to go out and about in London. To save myself from three weeks of Football Manager and repeats of The Office, I stocked up on cyber security books. I finally completed my first runthrough of the mammoth CISSP study guide, brushed up on my PowerShell with PowerShell for Sysadmins, and took some time to improve my Wireshark skills with Practical Packet Analysis. The latter was certainly my favourite - Chris Sanders’ book serves as both a very practical exploration of packet analysis and just about the best introduction to networking fundamentals I’ve come across. It’s certainly one I’ll be recommending to my colleagues when I return to the (virtual) office. When I finished Practical Packet Analysis, I decided I wanted to increase my familiarity not only with Wireshark and analysis techniques, but also how the packets are generated in the first place. It’s easy enough to run ping or nslookup and observe the results, but when it came to manually crafting packets I was only vaguely aware of where to start, and it seemed like a useful area to explore. So I fired up a couple of Linux virtual machines, opened Google, and got searching for tools and tutorials to help me. Below is a brief overview of some of the tools I experimented with. Some of them allow you to create packets, others TCP connections - but all of them are worth spending some time with to send some packets, generate some PCAPs, and learn more about how your network functions. Contents 1. netcat 2. Bash 3. Scapy 4. SendIp netcat Let’s start with a classic. A favourite among cyber security professionals, netcat is a tool that can be used to send and receive data between systems, either via TCP or via UDP with the -u flag. A listener is set up using the -l flag - for example, the command below would start a listener on UDP port 372. sudo nc -lu 372 With this system listening for UDP datagrams on port 372, we can now use netcat to send data from a second system. The command to begin sending data is quite similar to the one for setting up the listener - just this time we remove the -l flag and specify the IP address we want to transmit the data to. sudo nc -u 192.168.234.128 372 Any text that is sent over the new connection is displayed almost immediately in the terminal of the receiving machine, which is fine if you’re sitting watching the Linux terminal and waiting for quite a short message, as in the example communication between the two VMs below. The beauty of Linux, however, is that we can easily chain together commands to achieve more than they could individually. Let’s say we want to send an image file via netcat, for example. We can use &amp;gt; and | to read the contents of the file on the sending machine and save it on the receiving machine. To receive the image via a TCP connection on port 555, the recipient would use the following command. sudo nc -l 555 &amp;gt; received_image.png The sender would do almost the exact opposite, piping the contents of the original image file to the netcat connection in order to transmit it over the network to the recipient’s system. cat image_to_send.png | sudo nc 192.168.234.128 555 cat reads the contents of the image file, which are piped to our netcat connection. The receiving system sends the data received over the connection to its own image file, and when we check the file itself via the GUI we can see that the image data was successfully transmitted and saved to disk. These examples only scratch the surface of what is possible with netcat, and I’d encourage you to play around with it to see what it is capable of. SANS has a particularly handy cheat sheet with common commands and accepted flags and options to help you get started. Bash While we’re on the topic of sending messages and files over the network, it’s also worth noting that the Linux Bash terminal actually has a built-in capability for this using /dev/tcp/ and /dev/udp/. Simply add an IP address and port and send your data to this directory, and Linux will handle the rest. echo &quot;Hello. I'm sending this from the Linux terminal.&quot; &amp;gt; /dev/tcp/192.168.234.128/824 In this example, I’ve used echo to send a text message over the network, but I could equally have used cat and a filename to send a file like we did with netcat. A netcat listener on the recipient’s system receives the message and outputs it to the terminal as in our first netcat example. Did you notice the small difference in the output above? When all the data has been received, the TCP connection is closed and the listener stops. If we were expecting to receive more data later, we could use netcat’s -k flag, which would keep the listener active. The TCP connection is still closed when the transfer is complete, but the listener persists and allows the creation of additional TCP connections as they are needed in response to connection requests from clients. Another difference to using netcat to send data was that we did not need to use sudo to send data from a TCP port using /dev/tcp/ - useful to know for scenarios where there are restrictions in place. Scapy Now let’s move down a level and take a look at some tools for manually crafting packets. Scapy is a Python tool that allows you to send custom packets, individually manipulating fields and flags via a series of commands and options to send exactly the data you want - very useful for testing. Let’s say I want to check my Pi-hole DNS server is functioning correctly and returning responses when it receives queries. I can manually craft a DNS request for my domain, www.mattcasmith.net, using the following command within Scapy to specify fields like the destination address/port and DNS query. (dst=&quot;{pihole_ip}&quot;)/UDP(dport=53)/DNS(rd=1,qd=DNSQR(qname=&quot;www.mattcasmith.net&quot;)),verbose=0) I specify the Pi-hole’s IP address and the UDP port 53 (used for DNS) as the destination, and provide the domain to be queried with the qname parameter. If all goes well, Scapy will send the packet to the DNS server and print the packet it receives in response, as below. If we wanted to review this data in a nicer format, we could also have run Wireshark or tcpdump at the same time to generate a PCAP. By reviewing the response above, we can see that the Pi-hole has successfully returned a response. Between the DNSRR tags we can see that the DNS server has returned several IP addresses associated witht the domain, as we’d see in the output of a tool like nslookup or dig. SendIp Another means to the same end is SendIp - a Linux command line tool that enables you to craft custom packets in a similar way to Scapy. Rather than sending another DNS query, let’s go back to an earlier example and set up a netcat listener on UDP port 904 to receive a text message. sudo sendip -p ipv4 -is 192.168.234.130 -p udp -us 5070 -ud 904 -d &quot;This is a datagram sent with sendip from the command line.&quot; -v 192.168.234.128 The length of the SendIp command reflects the additional flexibility we have compared to when we sent a similar message with netcat. The -p flag sets our protocols - in this case IPv4 at the network layer and UDP at the transport layer - and after each we specify the contents of various header fields. Notice that SendIP allows us to set the IP source address manually with -is as well as the UDP source port with -us. In testing scenarios, including penetration tests, this would allow us to spoof packets from different machines, with much greater control over the packet and header contents than with netcat. Finally, the -d flag declares the contents of the packet payload - in this case the text message, which we can see in the output on the recipient’s system is received by the netcat listener. All of the tools and examples above represent different ways of sending data over a network from the Linux command line. While I used simple text and file exchanges to demonstrate how they work, these tools have many different features and options and can be used in much more complex scenarios. Hopefully this post has given you some idea of how they work and what they are capable of, and given you enough of a starting point to try some experiments of your own.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Technicolor TG582n router: The missing event logging manual</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2020/07/18/technicolor-tg582n-event-logging-manual" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Technicolor TG582n router&amp;#58; The missing event logging manual" /><published>2020-07-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2020/07/18/technicolor-tg582n-missing-event-logging-manual</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mattcasmith.net/2020/07/18/technicolor-tg582n-event-logging-manual">&lt;p&gt;What started as curiosity has turned into something of a labour of love. Online information about the Technicolor TG582n router’s event logging capabilities is scarce, and scattered across a number of forums. I’ve used that information along with some analysis of my own to compile this - the missing event logging manual - in the hope that it might help others to expore their routers’ event logs in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;contents&quot;&gt;Contents&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. &lt;a href=&quot;#background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
2. &lt;a href=&quot;#forwarding-technicolor-tg582n-event-logs&quot;&gt;Forwarding Technicolor TG582n event logs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
3. &lt;a href=&quot;#useful-events-from-the-technicolor-tg582n&quot;&gt;Useful events from the Technicolor TG582n&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
          a. &lt;a href=&quot;#internet-connection-events&quot;&gt;Internet connection events&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
          b. &lt;a href=&quot;#wifi-authentication-events&quot;&gt;WiFi authentication events&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
          c. &lt;a href=&quot;#admin-authentication-events&quot;&gt;Admin authentication events&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
          d. &lt;a href=&quot;#firewall-events&quot;&gt;Firewall events&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
          e. &lt;a href=&quot;#intrusion-detection-system-ids-events&quot;&gt;Intrusion detection system (IDS) events&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
4. &lt;a href=&quot;#example-investigation-using-technicolor-tg582n-events&quot;&gt;Example investigation using Technicolor TG582n events&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
5. &lt;a href=&quot;#contribute&quot;&gt;Contribute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Technicolor TG582n is a common sight in British homes - and, if internet forums are a fair reflection of reality, homes in several other countries, too. It is, or was, the default ADSL router for a number of internet service providers (ISPs) and seems to be a common option to distribute to customers on bog standard tariffs who haven’t earned the Home Hubs and Sky Hubs of this world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used this router for several years (hence why I had one laying around) and as I grew more interested in cyber security I remember searching around several times for any information I could find regarding its logging capabilities and finding very little. So with a little more digging and the additional knowledge I’ve gained via experience since then, I thought I might be able to assemble something of a manual for anyone still using this router who wants to explore its event log and monitor their network activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that mission in mind, and safe in the knowledge that even bricking the device would have no repercussions for my internet access now I had a new router, I set out to find how to gather logs from the Technicolor TG282n and to aggregate enough of them that I could give an overview of some of the most common events generated by the little box, which until then had been gathering dust in a cupboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;forwarding-technicolor-tg582n-event-logs&quot;&gt;Forwarding Technicolor TG582n event logs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there may not be a manual for the Technicolor TG582n router’s event logging capabilities, there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.manualslib.com/products/Technicolor-Tg582n-3530624.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a manual for its Telnet interface&lt;/a&gt;. That’s right - the manufacturer is forcing us to send our administrative credentials over an unencrypted protocol to configure the router, so make sure you don’t do this if there’s a chance anyone malicious is on your network. When we log in, we’re greeted with some nice ASCII art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/technicolor-tg582n.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beautiful. Now let’s turn our attention to turning on the event log. If you’re in a hurry and just want to grab recent events, you can use the command below to send whatever events are in the router’s cache to your analysis machine via syslog. Make sure you have something listening on port 514 to receive them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;syslog&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;msgbuf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;send&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dest&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we’re looking for something a little longer lasting. Luckily, the Technicolor TG582n has a system for managing event log rules and a series of commands to view the rules, add new rules, remove rules, and start and stop the logging service. To set all events to be transmitted via syslog regardless of the service that generated them or their severity, enter the following commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;syslog&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ruleadd&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fac&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;all&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sev&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;debug&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dest&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;syslog&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;syslog&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;config&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;activate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;enabled&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first command adds a syslog rule on the router. It gathers events from all facilities (or services) and at all severity levels (debug being the lowest) and transmits them via syslog to the destination IP address specified. The second command displays the list of syslog rules so we can make sure the rule was added correctly, and the final one enables the syslog service so events will begin to be transmitted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, this means that once again we’ll need a service listening on port 514 on the destination system. If you’re sending logs for a quick check then &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wireshark.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wireshark&lt;/a&gt; is probably enough. I was looking to gather events from a longer period of time to identify as many event types as possible, so I set up &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.elastic.co/logstash&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Logstash&lt;/a&gt; to receive the syslog and write the events to a file I could analyse later. A syslog server is another alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;useful-events-from-the-technicolor-tg582n&quot;&gt;Useful events from the Technicolor TG582n&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After leaving the syslog service and Logstash running for about a week, I opened the log file in Excel and manipulated the contents into a format that would enable me to filter them down to unique event types. What follows are some of the most useful and/or interesting events I picked out from the logs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;internet-connection-events&quot;&gt;Internet connection events&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the basics. Most times you check your router logs, you’re likely to be investigating connectivity issues and checking to see whether you have an internet connection. These events relating to the point-to-point protocol (PPP) will hopefully provide you with an answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PPP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;link&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;down&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Internet&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PPP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;CHAP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;receive&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;challenge&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rhost&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_hostname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PPP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;CHAP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;chap&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;receive&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;success&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;authentication&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ok&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PPP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;link&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;up&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Internet&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first event is the one you’ll hope not to see. As the &lt;code&gt;link down&lt;/code&gt; message suggests, this event is generated when your internet connection fails and you no longer have a connection to your ISP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next two events are generated when you try to reconnect and relate to the challenge-handshake authentication protocol (CHAP). Your router recieves an authentication challenge from your ISP, provides your credentials, and gets an &lt;code&gt;authentication ok&lt;/code&gt; response if everything checks out. Then you’ll see the final &lt;code&gt;link up&lt;/code&gt; event when the internet connection is back up and running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wifi-authentication-events&quot;&gt;WiFi authentication events&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as I started scanning the logs, one event stood out as potentially useful in catching perhaps the most common of wireless network attacks: unauthorised attempts to access the WiFi network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LOGIN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;wireless&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mac_address&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;can&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'t get authorized&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s some debate online about exactly what this event means, and people have seen it pop up in all sorts of unexpected ways (including one forum user whose stolen PlayStation 3 was apparently haunting his router and failing to connect to the network on a regular basis).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it sounds like it might refer to an access point, a “wireless station” in networking jargon is actually a device that can join the wireless network. In my case these events all featured the MAC address of an Apple device - and not one of my own - so that would be an obvious one to block, just to be safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;admin-authentication-events&quot;&gt;Admin authentication events&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bread and butter of security event logging is authentication: who is logging in and out of your system and who is failing to log in using an incorrect password? This is doubly important for admin accounts, and the Technicolor TG582n’s syslog has got you covered with a few takes on these common events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LOGIN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;User&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;username&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;logged&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;on&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TELNET&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LOGOUT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;User&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;username&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;logged&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;out&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;on&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TELNET&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LOGIN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;User&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;username&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tried&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;on&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TELNET&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;SESSION&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TIMEOUT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Timeout&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;after&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;600&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sec&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first two events are what you would expect to see for a normal administrative session - one for when the user logs in and one for when they log out. The important thing is that Technicolor has included the username and the source IP address, which are key details if you’re planning to apply any kind of detection logic to these logs or even manually trying to investigate potential attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third event is misleading. A user “tried to” log in? Many devices would follow this up with an authentication success or failure event, but in this case it actually signifies a failed login by itself. Unfortunately, while we again get the username and source IP address, we do not get one critical detail: whether the failure was due to a bad username or an incorrect password.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we have an event that may help to track user sessions that do not end with a &lt;code&gt;LOGOUT&lt;/code&gt; event. When the Telnet connection is left idle for a while, the Technicolor TG582n eventually closes it, and it seems that’s when this event is created. It’s unlikely to pop up too often, but still potentially useful to know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;firewall-events&quot;&gt;Firewall events&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The firewall is in charge of allowing or denying traffic based on its source and destination and the connection type. First up, here the the events that the Technicolor TG582n generates when somebody makes changes to its firewall rules. As you can see, they’re fairly self-explanatory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FIREWALL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;event&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;created&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rules&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FIREWALL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;event&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;modified&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rules&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FIREWALL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;event&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;deleted&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rules&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might suspect, these are generated when firewall rules are created, modified, and deleted respectively. One thing to watch out for with these, however, is that all three events seem to be generated in this order when a connection to the internet is established. So don’t be surprised if you see them crop up at points in the logs that you weren’t expecting them if the router was connecting to your ISP. Their effect will also require some investigation, as they don’t actually state &lt;em&gt;which&lt;/em&gt; rules were changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, let’s look at the firewall in action. In the week the router was active, the firewall sprung into action on the following three occasions, all of which related to internet control message protocol (ICMP) traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FIREWALL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;replay&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;check&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Protocol&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ICMP&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Src&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Dst&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Destination&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Unreachable&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Code&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Port&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Unreacheable&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FIREWALL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;icmp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;check&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Protocol&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ICMP&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Src&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Dst&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Destination&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Unreachable&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Code&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Port&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Unreacheable&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FIREWALL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;icmp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;check&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Protocol&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ICMP&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Src&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Dst&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Reply&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Code&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately there’s no authority on what these actually mean. I’d expect a “replay check” to attempt to stop replay attacks, but the leading theory on the forums seems to be that this event means the firewall has prevented your router from providing a response to an ICMP ping from an attacker performing reconnaissance and attempting to discover information about your network. I have, however, also seen this occurring on outbound traffic to DNS servers from &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/02/15/pi-hole-samsung-smart-tv/&quot;&gt;my Pi-hole&lt;/a&gt;, so your guess is as good as mine and any additional information anyone might be able to share would be appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;intrusion-detection-system-ids-events&quot;&gt;Intrusion detection system (IDS) events&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a reason they say to start with your home network if you want to learn about cyber security. Looking through the IDS log will give you a nice insight into all the potentially nasty stuff targeting your network and give you a newfound appreciation for all the work your little Technicolor TG582n does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;IDS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dos&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;parser&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;idp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;flood&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0801&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;UDP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;IDS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rate&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;parser&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tcp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rate&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;limiting&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0040&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TCP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;S&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.....]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;seq&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;win&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1024&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;IDS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scan&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;parser&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tcp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;port&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scanned&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;at&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;least&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ports&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;at&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0040&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TCP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;..]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;seq&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;11694198&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;win&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;IDS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scan&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;parser&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;udp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;port&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scanned&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;at&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;least&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ports&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;at&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0441&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;UDP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;IDS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scan&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;parser&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tcp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;syn&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scanned&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;at&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;least&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ports&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;at&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0040&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TCP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;S&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.....]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;seq&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;97417629&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;win&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1024&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;IDS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;proto&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;parser&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tcp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;null&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;port&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0040&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TCP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;S&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.....]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;seq&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2505992964&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;win&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1024&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IDS appears to have detection rules for potential denial of service (DoS) attacks. In the first event, too many UDP packets were detected between the same IP addresses. This typically appears to be followed up by a UDP rate limiting event as the router attempts to protect the network against the perceived attack. What’s pretty cool is that this also appears to apply to outgoing traffic, so if your devices become infected and form part of a botnet they are prevented from spamming the attackers’ targets with packets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second event in my sample concerns TCP rate limiting and in my logs was applied to an IP address from Russia. An IDS applies rate limiting when it receives a large number of connection requests from a particular IP address and applies a temporary block to avoid a denial of service (DoS) condition. Note that this wouldn’t stop a distributed denial of service (DDoS) attack, which achieves the same result by sending a smaller number of packets from each of a large number of IP addresses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we have various types of detected port scans - in my case detected from IP addresses belonging to organisations as varied as Akamai, Amazon, GoDaddy, and Twitch, as well as a few IP addresses that looked like Russian hackers. Not much you can do about that, but it’s interesting stuff nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we have a TCP null port packet detection (in my logs the destination port showed up as 0). I couldn’t find too much information about this, but it’s likely to be a sign that an attacker is crafting nonsensical packets in an attempt to elicit an abnormal response from the router.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;example-investigation-using-technicolor-tg582n-events&quot;&gt;Example investigation using Technicolor TG582n events&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where does knowing all this get you? Having visibility of your router events and understanding what they mean can help you to troubleshoot network issues and identify potential cyber attacks - anything from sophisticated intruders to neighbours hijacking your broadband connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example of how the Technicolor TG582n’s event logs can come in useful, during the week I was running the router I noticed a potential problem. Like many others during the COVID-19 pandemic, I was working from home, and my Skype video calls would drop out seemingly randomly. I decided to do some digging in the new logs for any clues, and here’s what I found at around the time of one of my failed calls…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;IDS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dos&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;parser&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;udp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;flood&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;my_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;company_server_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0801&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;UDP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;IDS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rate&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;parser&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;udp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rate&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;limiting&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;my_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;company_server_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1072&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;UDP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;source_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destination_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PPP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;link&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;down&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Internet&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;my_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PPP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;CHAP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Receive&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;challenge&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rhost&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;host&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PPP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;CHAP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Chap&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;receive&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;success&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;authentication&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ok&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PPP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;link&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;up&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Internet&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;my_ip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My best theory is this: The router spotted the large number of UDP datagrams being sent between my system and the Skype server and assumed this was a DoS attack. To put a stop to it, it applied rate limiting to the connection, which disrupted the call. Somewhere along the line this upset &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;, and that &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; failing took the connection down, meaning I had to wait for the broadband connection to resume before signing back into Skype, reconnecting to the call, and giving my apologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there’s little that you could do about this particular issue. The Technicolor TG582n gives you the option of turning the IDS on or off, and there is no configuration to be done beyond that - you’re either protected or you’re not. I suppose that means I should be glad that I’ve since upgraded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;contribute&quot;&gt;Contribute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Event enumeration without proper documentation is often very hit-and-miss. I left the Technicolor TG582n router running for about a week to generate as many different events as possible, but if a certain type of event simply didn’t occur, it won’t have shown up in my analysis. If you have important and/or interesting events to add to this list, please get in touch via the links below and I’ll add them in (with credit!).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><category term="Networking" /><category term="Internet" /><category term="Router" /><category term="Logs" /><category term="IDS" /><category term="Firewall" /><summary type="html">What started as curiosity has turned into something of a labour of love. Online information about the Technicolor TG582n router’s event logging capabilities is scarce, and scattered across a number of forums. I’ve used that information along with some analysis of my own to compile this - the missing event logging manual - in the hope that it might help others to expore their routers’ event logs in future. Contents 1. Background 2. Forwarding Technicolor TG582n event logs 3. Useful events from the Technicolor TG582n           a. Internet connection events           b. WiFi authentication events           c. Admin authentication events           d. Firewall events           e. Intrusion detection system (IDS) events 4. Example investigation using Technicolor TG582n events 5. Contribute Background The Technicolor TG582n is a common sight in British homes - and, if internet forums are a fair reflection of reality, homes in several other countries, too. It is, or was, the default ADSL router for a number of internet service providers (ISPs) and seems to be a common option to distribute to customers on bog standard tariffs who haven’t earned the Home Hubs and Sky Hubs of this world. I used this router for several years (hence why I had one laying around) and as I grew more interested in cyber security I remember searching around several times for any information I could find regarding its logging capabilities and finding very little. So with a little more digging and the additional knowledge I’ve gained via experience since then, I thought I might be able to assemble something of a manual for anyone still using this router who wants to explore its event log and monitor their network activity. With that mission in mind, and safe in the knowledge that even bricking the device would have no repercussions for my internet access now I had a new router, I set out to find how to gather logs from the Technicolor TG282n and to aggregate enough of them that I could give an overview of some of the most common events generated by the little box, which until then had been gathering dust in a cupboard. Forwarding Technicolor TG582n event logs While there may not be a manual for the Technicolor TG582n router’s event logging capabilities, there is a manual for its Telnet interface. That’s right - the manufacturer is forcing us to send our administrative credentials over an unencrypted protocol to configure the router, so make sure you don’t do this if there’s a chance anyone malicious is on your network. When we log in, we’re greeted with some nice ASCII art. Beautiful. Now let’s turn our attention to turning on the event log. If you’re in a hurry and just want to grab recent events, you can use the command below to send whatever events are in the router’s cache to your analysis machine via syslog. Make sure you have something listening on port 514 to receive them. syslog msgbuf send dest=&amp;lt;destination_ip&amp;gt; But we’re looking for something a little longer lasting. Luckily, the Technicolor TG582n has a system for managing event log rules and a series of commands to view the rules, add new rules, remove rules, and start and stop the logging service. To set all events to be transmitted via syslog regardless of the service that generated them or their severity, enter the following commands. syslog ruleadd fac=all sev=debug dest=&amp;lt;destination_ip&amp;gt; syslog list syslog config activate=enabled The first command adds a syslog rule on the router. It gathers events from all facilities (or services) and at all severity levels (debug being the lowest) and transmits them via syslog to the destination IP address specified. The second command displays the list of syslog rules so we can make sure the rule was added correctly, and the final one enables the syslog service so events will begin to be transmitted. Naturally, this means that once again we’ll need a service listening on port 514 on the destination system. If you’re sending logs for a quick check then Wireshark is probably enough. I was looking to gather events from a longer period of time to identify as many event types as possible, so I set up Logstash to receive the syslog and write the events to a file I could analyse later. A syslog server is another alternative. Useful events from the Technicolor TG582n After leaving the syslog service and Logstash running for about a week, I opened the log file in Excel and manipulated the contents into a format that would enable me to filter them down to unique event types. What follows are some of the most useful and/or interesting events I picked out from the logs. Internet connection events Let’s start with the basics. Most times you check your router logs, you’re likely to be investigating connectivity issues and checking to see whether you have an internet connection. These events relating to the point-to-point protocol (PPP) will hopefully provide you with an answer. PPP link down (Internet) [&amp;lt;source_ip&amp;gt;] PPP CHAP receive challenge (rhost = &amp;lt;destination_hostname&amp;gt;) PPP CHAP chap receive success : authentication ok PPP link up (Internet) [&amp;lt;source_ip&amp;gt;] The first event is the one you’ll hope not to see. As the link down message suggests, this event is generated when your internet connection fails and you no longer have a connection to your ISP. The next two events are generated when you try to reconnect and relate to the challenge-handshake authentication protocol (CHAP). Your router recieves an authentication challenge from your ISP, provides your credentials, and gets an authentication ok response if everything checks out. Then you’ll see the final link up event when the internet connection is back up and running. WiFi authentication events As soon as I started scanning the logs, one event stood out as potentially useful in catching perhaps the most common of wireless network attacks: unauthorised attempts to access the WiFi network. LOGIN wireless station [&amp;lt;mac_address&amp;gt;] can't get authorized There’s some debate online about exactly what this event means, and people have seen it pop up in all sorts of unexpected ways (including one forum user whose stolen PlayStation 3 was apparently haunting his router and failing to connect to the network on a regular basis). Although it sounds like it might refer to an access point, a “wireless station” in networking jargon is actually a device that can join the wireless network. In my case these events all featured the MAC address of an Apple device - and not one of my own - so that would be an obvious one to block, just to be safe. Admin authentication events The bread and butter of security event logging is authentication: who is logging in and out of your system and who is failing to log in using an incorrect password? This is doubly important for admin accounts, and the Technicolor TG582n’s syslog has got you covered with a few takes on these common events. LOGIN User &amp;lt;username&amp;gt; logged in on TELNET (&amp;lt;source_ip&amp;gt;) LOGOUT User &amp;lt;username&amp;gt; logged out on TELNET (&amp;lt;source_ip&amp;gt;) LOGIN User &amp;lt;username&amp;gt; tried to log in on TELNET (&amp;lt;source_ip&amp;gt;) SESSION TIMEOUT Timeout! (after 600 sec) The first two events are what you would expect to see for a normal administrative session - one for when the user logs in and one for when they log out. The important thing is that Technicolor has included the username and the source IP address, which are key details if you’re planning to apply any kind of detection logic to these logs or even manually trying to investigate potential attacks. The third event is misleading. A user “tried to” log in? Many devices would follow this up with an authentication success or failure event, but in this case it actually signifies a failed login by itself. Unfortunately, while we again get the username and source IP address, we do not get one critical detail: whether the failure was due to a bad username or an incorrect password. Finally, we have an event that may help to track user sessions that do not end with a LOGOUT event. When the Telnet connection is left idle for a while, the Technicolor TG582n eventually closes it, and it seems that’s when this event is created. It’s unlikely to pop up too often, but still potentially useful to know. Firewall events The firewall is in charge of allowing or denying traffic based on its source and destination and the connection type. First up, here the the events that the Technicolor TG582n generates when somebody makes changes to its firewall rules. As you can see, they’re fairly self-explanatory. FIREWALL event (x of x): created rules FIREWALL event (x of x): modified rules FIREWALL event (x of x): deleted rules As you might suspect, these are generated when firewall rules are created, modified, and deleted respectively. One thing to watch out for with these, however, is that all three events seem to be generated in this order when a connection to the internet is established. So don’t be surprised if you see them crop up at points in the logs that you weren’t expecting them if the router was connecting to your ISP. Their effect will also require some investigation, as they don’t actually state which rules were changed. Next, let’s look at the firewall in action. In the week the router was active, the firewall sprung into action on the following three occasions, all of which related to internet control message protocol (ICMP) traffic. FIREWALL replay check (&amp;lt;x&amp;gt; of &amp;lt;x&amp;gt;): Protocol: ICMP Src ip: &amp;lt;source_ip&amp;gt; Dst ip: &amp;lt;destination_ip&amp;gt; Type: Destination Unreachable Code: Port Unreacheable FIREWALL icmp check (&amp;lt;x&amp;gt; of &amp;lt;x&amp;gt;): Protocol: ICMP Src ip: &amp;lt;source_ip&amp;gt; Dst ip: &amp;lt;destination_ip&amp;gt; Type: Destination Unreachable Code: Port Unreacheable FIREWALL icmp check (&amp;lt;x&amp;gt; of &amp;lt;x&amp;gt;): Protocol: ICMP Src ip: &amp;lt;source_ip&amp;gt; Dst ip: &amp;lt;destination_ip&amp;gt; Type: Echo Reply Code: 0 Unfortunately there’s no authority on what these actually mean. I’d expect a “replay check” to attempt to stop replay attacks, but the leading theory on the forums seems to be that this event means the firewall has prevented your router from providing a response to an ICMP ping from an attacker performing reconnaissance and attempting to discover information about your network. I have, however, also seen this occurring on outbound traffic to DNS servers from my Pi-hole, so your guess is as good as mine and any additional information anyone might be able to share would be appreciated. Intrusion detection system (IDS) events There’s a reason they say to start with your home network if you want to learn about cyber security. Looking through the IDS log will give you a nice insight into all the potentially nasty stuff targeting your network and give you a newfound appreciation for all the work your little Technicolor TG582n does. IDS dos parser : idp flood (1 of 1) : &amp;lt;source_ip&amp;gt; &amp;lt;destination_ip&amp;gt; 0801 UDP &amp;lt;source_port&amp;gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;lt;destination_port&amp;gt; IDS rate parser : tcp rate limiting (1 of 1) : &amp;lt;source_ip&amp;gt; &amp;lt;destination_ip&amp;gt; 0040 TCP &amp;lt;source_port&amp;gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;lt;destination_port&amp;gt; [S.....] seq 100 win 1024 IDS scan parser : tcp port scan: &amp;lt;destination_ip&amp;gt; scanned at least 10 ports at &amp;lt;destination_ip&amp;gt;. (1 of 1) : &amp;lt;source_ip&amp;gt; &amp;lt;destination_ip&amp;gt; 0040 TCP &amp;lt;source_port&amp;gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;lt;destination_port&amp;gt; [...R..] seq 11694198 win 0 IDS scan parser : udp port scan: &amp;lt;source_ip&amp;gt; scanned at least 20 ports at &amp;lt;destination_ip&amp;gt;. (1 of 1) : &amp;lt;source_ip&amp;gt; &amp;lt;destination_ip&amp;gt; 0441 UDP &amp;lt;source_port&amp;gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;lt;destination_port&amp;gt; IDS scan parser : tcp syn scan: &amp;lt;source_ip&amp;gt; scanned at least 20 ports at &amp;lt;destination_ip&amp;gt;. (1 of 1) : &amp;lt;source_ip&amp;gt; &amp;lt;destination_ip&amp;gt; 0040 TCP &amp;lt;source_port&amp;gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;lt;destination_port&amp;gt; [S.....] seq 97417629 win 1024 IDS proto parser : tcp null port (1 of 1) : &amp;lt;source_ip&amp;gt; &amp;lt;destination_ip&amp;gt; 0040 TCP &amp;lt;source_port&amp;gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;lt;destination_port&amp;gt; [S.....] seq 2505992964 win 1024 The IDS appears to have detection rules for potential denial of service (DoS) attacks. In the first event, too many UDP packets were detected between the same IP addresses. This typically appears to be followed up by a UDP rate limiting event as the router attempts to protect the network against the perceived attack. What’s pretty cool is that this also appears to apply to outgoing traffic, so if your devices become infected and form part of a botnet they are prevented from spamming the attackers’ targets with packets. The second event in my sample concerns TCP rate limiting and in my logs was applied to an IP address from Russia. An IDS applies rate limiting when it receives a large number of connection requests from a particular IP address and applies a temporary block to avoid a denial of service (DoS) condition. Note that this wouldn’t stop a distributed denial of service (DDoS) attack, which achieves the same result by sending a smaller number of packets from each of a large number of IP addresses. Then we have various types of detected port scans - in my case detected from IP addresses belonging to organisations as varied as Akamai, Amazon, GoDaddy, and Twitch, as well as a few IP addresses that looked like Russian hackers. Not much you can do about that, but it’s interesting stuff nonetheless. Finally, we have a TCP null port packet detection (in my logs the destination port showed up as 0). I couldn’t find too much information about this, but it’s likely to be a sign that an attacker is crafting nonsensical packets in an attempt to elicit an abnormal response from the router. Example investigation using Technicolor TG582n events Where does knowing all this get you? Having visibility of your router events and understanding what they mean can help you to troubleshoot network issues and identify potential cyber attacks - anything from sophisticated intruders to neighbours hijacking your broadband connection. As an example of how the Technicolor TG582n’s event logs can come in useful, during the week I was running the router I noticed a potential problem. Like many others during the COVID-19 pandemic, I was working from home, and my Skype video calls would drop out seemingly randomly. I decided to do some digging in the new logs for any clues, and here’s what I found at around the time of one of my failed calls… IDS dos parser : udp flood (1 of 1): &amp;lt;my_ip&amp;gt; &amp;lt;company_server_ip&amp;gt; 0801 UDP &amp;lt;source_port&amp;gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;lt;destination_port&amp;gt; IDS rate parser : udp rate limiting (1 of 1): &amp;lt;my_ip&amp;gt; &amp;lt;company_server_ip&amp;gt; 1072 UDP &amp;lt;source_port&amp;gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;lt;destination_port&amp;gt; PPP link down (Internet) [&amp;lt;my_ip&amp;gt;] PPP CHAP Receive challenge (rhost = &amp;lt;host&amp;gt;) PPP CHAP Chap receive success : authentication ok PPP link up (Internet) [&amp;lt;my_ip&amp;gt;] My best theory is this: The router spotted the large number of UDP datagrams being sent between my system and the Skype server and assumed this was a DoS attack. To put a stop to it, it applied rate limiting to the connection, which disrupted the call. Somewhere along the line this upset something, and that something failing took the connection down, meaning I had to wait for the broadband connection to resume before signing back into Skype, reconnecting to the call, and giving my apologies. Unfortunately, there’s little that you could do about this particular issue. The Technicolor TG582n gives you the option of turning the IDS on or off, and there is no configuration to be done beyond that - you’re either protected or you’re not. I suppose that means I should be glad that I’ve since upgraded. Contribute Event enumeration without proper documentation is often very hit-and-miss. I left the Technicolor TG582n router running for about a week to generate as many different events as possible, but if a certain type of event simply didn’t occur, it won’t have shown up in my analysis. If you have important and/or interesting events to add to this list, please get in touch via the links below and I’ll add them in (with credit!).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/technicolor-tg582n-router.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/technicolor-tg582n-router.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to a new website with a new philosophy</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2020/06/30/new-website-new-philosophy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to a new website with a new philosophy" /><published>2020-07-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2020/06/30/new-website-new-philosophy%20-%20Copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mattcasmith.net/2020/06/30/new-website-new-philosophy/">&lt;p&gt;You may have noticed that things have changed around here - I built a new website, following the ethos that it should be as clear, lightweight, and fast as possible while respecting visitors’ privacy by keeping outside scripts and tracking to a minimum. In this post I take you through the process of designing and building the new site, from the initial inspiration to the end product you see today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read a lot of books during the COVID-19 lockdown. These ranged from one of the best novels I’ve ever read (&lt;em&gt;South of the Border, West of the Sun&lt;/em&gt; by Haruki Murakami) to some more relaxing non-fiction (&lt;em&gt;Blood, Sweat, and Pixels&lt;/em&gt; by Jason Schreier). But the pick of the bunch, and the one that has inspired me the most, is &lt;em&gt;Chaos Monkeys: Mayhem and Mania Inside the Silicon Valley Machine&lt;/em&gt;, which charts Antonio Garcia Martinez’s journey from Goldman Sachs to start-up founder to Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of this book goes beyond what is physically held within its pages. Martinez referenced so many Googlable concepts, companies, people, and blogs that the thing took me about twice as long to read as any other book (perhaps the best among these was Paul Graham’s blog post &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/start.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;How to Start a Startup&lt;a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which Martinez described as “a crack-like gateway drug to the startup addiction”).&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without a doubt the most valuable outcome of reading Martinez’s memoir, however, was that it reconnected me with &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;. Hacker News is a website run by the start-up accelerator Y Combinator. It functions something like Reddit, with hackers (read: people who like to code and make stuff, not hoodie-wearing, basement-dwelling script kiddies) posting links and upvoting useful content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By proxy, reconnecting with Hacker News meant reconnecting with the wonderful world of personal blogs run by techy people. I always try to pick up on these because they offer more inspiration and insight than commercial websites, but on the regular internet links to them are few and far between - something I’m acutely aware of with my own blog, which occasionally receives thousands of views in a short space of time thanks to Reddit posts, but does not do too well via search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another big influence on the project was a series of blog posts I read on the concept of web bloat, including the transcript of Maciej Ceglowski’s talk &lt;a href=&quot;https://idlewords.com/talks/website_obesity.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Website Obesity Crisis&lt;/a&gt;, which laments all the unnecessary additions to web pages that slow everything down and reduce compatibility without tangible benefit to the user. This leads to short news article pages that have bigger file sizes than the full text of &lt;em&gt;War and Peace&lt;/em&gt;, and misguided initiatives like Google’s Accelerated Mobile Pages (AMP) that speed up page loads but are still bloated and only serve to tighten big tech’s stranglehold on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been mulling a change of platform - or rather a change away from my previous platform - for quite some time. After all, I am a cyber security professional, and for all its merits WordPress (or at least its plethora of poorly-coded plug-ins) sprouts as many vulnerabilities each month as the most detested corporate software out there. Add to that the overhead of dynamically generating every page as it is requested, which isn’t strictly necessary for a blog that is updated at most once per month, and it was clear that there was a better, more efficient way to do things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;objectives&quot;&gt;Objectives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that, I decided to take some inspiration from these small hacker blogs and build something new. But before I started, I needed to think carefully about exacly what I wanted to achieve and how I would do it. The following is a summary of what I came up with, embellished with the wisdom of hindsight:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The site should serve lightweight, static pages.&lt;/strong&gt; In the interest of speed and efficiency, it was time to say goodbye to dynamically generated pages like those served by WordPress. They just take too long when good old HTML and CSS could do just as good a job by themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The site should give me control.&lt;/strong&gt; I’m a (fairly) competent person. I don’t need to be restricted by WordPress themes to avoid breaking my website. If I want to add new page elements or try out new features I should have the freedom to do so without worrying about how they fit into a content management system’s ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The site should scale back user tracking.&lt;/strong&gt; At various points in the past I’ve used Google Analytics and Jetpack to count visits. I’m still interested in how many people read my blog posts, but those solutions gave me more analytics than I would ever need, and stripping that bloat away could also negate the need for an ugly, annoying EU cookie notice.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The site should save me money.&lt;/strong&gt; I’d been stuck with the same web hosting provider since 2012. To be fair they were relatively cheap, but when I needed support it was often sub-par and I frequently had to nag them to implement basic things like PHP updates. For the new website I’d be keeping an eye out for a new host, potentially even with a free platform that would support such a basic site.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With those broad goals in mind, I grabbed a pen and paper and spent some of my early time in lockdown sketching out what such a website might look like and listing ideas for how to satisfy my self-imposed requirements. After a little thinking and a bit of research, I had a plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;building-the-site&quot;&gt;Building the site&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My initial idea to scratch my minimalist itch was to develop a series of Python scripts that would take data from text files, format them according to some HTML templates, and publish them to my web server. Then I discovered &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, which already did all of that - and it’s much better, and has many more features, than what I would have developed. What’s not to love about open source?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I downloaded it, got it running on Linux for Windows, and built the website you’re now reading. While it is a little more complicated than this makes it sound (Jekyll lets you store common elements in separate files and call them, and uses WordPress-style loops for posts, categories, and page content), the page you’re reading now is pure HTML and CSS, lovingly crafted from the ground up with the goal of staying as minimalist as possible. After running some page load tests, I think I’ve succeeded there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some cool features in here that I’m quite proud of. For a start, the site is responsive and looks great on mobile (the way the homepage achieves this is slightly hacky, but I’ll probably revisit that later). It also respects your preference for light or dark mode and displays the site in the appropriate colours (I use dark mode myself, so if there are light mode bugs I haven’t spotted, please let me know).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it perfect? No. Every so often I spot a styling bug, the meta side of things could probably do with a once over, and there are definitely some messy elements to the code that I’d like to come up with more elegant solutions for in future. But in the spirit of moving fast and breaking things, the minimum viable product you see before you functions perfectly well in displaying information provided by me to you, the reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other area where I could be more efficient is my use of Jekyll. Being new to the whole thing, I learnt how it functions as I built the site, which is fine, but means there are probably a lot of things I would do differently now I’m more experienced. The great thing about Jekyll, however, is that because it builds static HTML pages, the output is all that matters for the most part, and poor input isn’t going to introduce any security vulnerabilities to the website because… well, there’s nothing to hack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hosting-the-site&quot;&gt;Hosting the site&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I had something to share with the world, I needed somewhere to share it from. A bunch of HTML pages could be hosted anywhere, and the easiest thing to do would have been to stick with my previous hosting provider. But by chance I came across a discussion about &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; - a free platform for personal and project sites - and thought it sounded like a great solution to my problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With GitHub Pages, I could save some money while taking a bet that Microsoft-owned servers would be faster and more reliable than my previous provider’s. I could use my own domain, and the transition even gave me a security boost as my domain and my site files are now behind separate 2FA-enabled logins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setup, I’ll admit, was a little fiddly. GitHub Pages is not terribly well documented besides some basic instructions, and it seems to take a while to propagate once you turn it on. Eventually I got there, however, and the pain of the initial configuration is likely to be worth the ease with which I can publish new blog posts and other changes - simply by committing changes to a GitHub repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adapting-my-content&quot;&gt;Adapting my content&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One slightly time-consuming task was updating all my WordPress content to fit the new Jekyll site. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://wordpress.org/plugins/jekyll-exporter/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jekyll Exporter plug-in&lt;/a&gt; was invaluable in this, saving me a lot of time manually copying posts into markdown by exporting all my WordPress posts into a Jekyll-friendly format… mostly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work that remained was still tedious. WordPress had automatically replaced all images in the body text of my posts with source addresses on its content delivery network, so I needed to replace them with the URLs of the images on my web server. Also, I’d been using a plug-in to highlight code on my WordPress site, so I needed to go through all my programming posts and wrap the code in the Jekyll tags that would apply the right formatting. This wasn’t a difficult task, but it was long-winded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My internet minimalism didn’t stop at the design, however. I’m also more conscious than ever that I want every page on my website to offer value to readers. This doesn’t mean &lt;a href=&quot;/category/off-topic.html&quot;&gt;the Off-Topic category&lt;/a&gt; is going anywhere - value isn’t limited by subject. But at some points in the past I’ve been very determined to write a blog post every two weeks, or every month, and when inspiration didn’t strike this led to some bland posts. I removed these, keeping only what I see as the higher-value posts, and I will endeavour to ensure all future posts are based around either an interesting take or useful technical content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tracking-the-site&quot;&gt;Tracking the site&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what about the elephant in the room: tracking? As I previously mentioned, some of the data provided by Google Analytics and Jetpack was useful, but it went far beyond what I needed and their use of cookies meant I needed a warning on the site to comply with EU law - something that jarred with my minimalist objective. But what else was out there? Would I need to code a tracker myself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a period of weeks a few different analytics start-ups flaunted their offerings on Hacker News, but they were all aimed at enterprises and priced accordingly, meaning that an analytics implementation would set me back the money I was saving on hosting (and then some). It was looking like I’d need to bite the bullet and go back to Google if I wanted any insight into which of my posts visitors enjoyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goatcounter.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Goat Counter&lt;/a&gt;, which really saved the day on this. This open source analytics platform is free for personal use (although I’ll still probably buy the creators a coffee later on, once I’m sure it’s for me), and it uses a single JavaScript file to generate simple statistics: pages visited, referrers, countries, browsers, screeen size, and so on. It’s just the level of detail I need to keep improving the site, and it’s delivered with barely any tradeoff in terms of speed or user privacy. There are no cookies, either!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, this has worked out pretty well. The site loads quickly, and the process for creating a new post is both more straightforward and more flexible than it was under WordPress. It looks something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;        &lt;strong&gt;1.&lt;/strong&gt; Write post in Markdown format&lt;br /&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;2.&lt;/strong&gt; Run Jekyll to generate HTML pages&lt;br /&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;3.&lt;/strong&gt; Copy HTML to GitHub repository folder&lt;br /&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;4.&lt;/strong&gt; Push update to GitHub to publish&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The additional benefit of no paid hosting only sweetens the deal, and means that all I need to pay for is my domain. And I don’t even need to remember to back up my website anymore, because: a) it’s stored on GitHub, a more reliable platform than my previous provider; and b) the latest HTML files generated by Jekyll will always be on my hard drive, where they will be automatically picked up by my usual backups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s taken a lot of work, and probably would have taken a lot longer if it wasn’t for the extra time afforded by the COVID-19 lockdown, but overall I think I can call the project a success. I now have a light, fast-loading website that respects users’ privacy and better reflects who I am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are changes to be made and features I want to add, but the beauty of the Jekyll/GitHub setup is that I can continue to develop at my own pace and the site will still function. I’m also interested in any feedback visitors might have about the change, so if you have any thoughts, ideas, or suggestions for updates, please do use the links below to get in touch.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><category term="HTML" /><category term="CSS" /><category term="Web" /><category term="Internet" /><category term="Blogging" /><summary type="html">You may have noticed that things have changed around here - I built a new website, following the ethos that it should be as clear, lightweight, and fast as possible while respecting visitors’ privacy by keeping outside scripts and tracking to a minimum. In this post I take you through the process of designing and building the new site, from the initial inspiration to the end product you see today. Background I read a lot of books during the COVID-19 lockdown. These ranged from one of the best novels I’ve ever read (South of the Border, West of the Sun by Haruki Murakami) to some more relaxing non-fiction (Blood, Sweat, and Pixels by Jason Schreier). But the pick of the bunch, and the one that has inspired me the most, is Chaos Monkeys: Mayhem and Mania Inside the Silicon Valley Machine, which charts Antonio Garcia Martinez’s journey from Goldman Sachs to start-up founder to Facebook. The value of this book goes beyond what is physically held within its pages. Martinez referenced so many Googlable concepts, companies, people, and blogs that the thing took me about twice as long to read as any other book (perhaps the best among these was Paul Graham’s blog post How to Start a Startup, which Martinez described as “a crack-like gateway drug to the startup addiction”). Without a doubt the most valuable outcome of reading Martinez’s memoir, however, was that it reconnected me with Hacker News. Hacker News is a website run by the start-up accelerator Y Combinator. It functions something like Reddit, with hackers (read: people who like to code and make stuff, not hoodie-wearing, basement-dwelling script kiddies) posting links and upvoting useful content. By proxy, reconnecting with Hacker News meant reconnecting with the wonderful world of personal blogs run by techy people. I always try to pick up on these because they offer more inspiration and insight than commercial websites, but on the regular internet links to them are few and far between - something I’m acutely aware of with my own blog, which occasionally receives thousands of views in a short space of time thanks to Reddit posts, but does not do too well via search. Another big influence on the project was a series of blog posts I read on the concept of web bloat, including the transcript of Maciej Ceglowski’s talk The Website Obesity Crisis, which laments all the unnecessary additions to web pages that slow everything down and reduce compatibility without tangible benefit to the user. This leads to short news article pages that have bigger file sizes than the full text of War and Peace, and misguided initiatives like Google’s Accelerated Mobile Pages (AMP) that speed up page loads but are still bloated and only serve to tighten big tech’s stranglehold on the internet. I had been mulling a change of platform - or rather a change away from my previous platform - for quite some time. After all, I am a cyber security professional, and for all its merits WordPress (or at least its plethora of poorly-coded plug-ins) sprouts as many vulnerabilities each month as the most detested corporate software out there. Add to that the overhead of dynamically generating every page as it is requested, which isn’t strictly necessary for a blog that is updated at most once per month, and it was clear that there was a better, more efficient way to do things. Objectives With that, I decided to take some inspiration from these small hacker blogs and build something new. But before I started, I needed to think carefully about exacly what I wanted to achieve and how I would do it. The following is a summary of what I came up with, embellished with the wisdom of hindsight: The site should serve lightweight, static pages. In the interest of speed and efficiency, it was time to say goodbye to dynamically generated pages like those served by WordPress. They just take too long when good old HTML and CSS could do just as good a job by themselves. The site should give me control. I’m a (fairly) competent person. I don’t need to be restricted by WordPress themes to avoid breaking my website. If I want to add new page elements or try out new features I should have the freedom to do so without worrying about how they fit into a content management system’s ecosystem. The site should scale back user tracking. At various points in the past I’ve used Google Analytics and Jetpack to count visits. I’m still interested in how many people read my blog posts, but those solutions gave me more analytics than I would ever need, and stripping that bloat away could also negate the need for an ugly, annoying EU cookie notice. The site should save me money. I’d been stuck with the same web hosting provider since 2012. To be fair they were relatively cheap, but when I needed support it was often sub-par and I frequently had to nag them to implement basic things like PHP updates. For the new website I’d be keeping an eye out for a new host, potentially even with a free platform that would support such a basic site. With those broad goals in mind, I grabbed a pen and paper and spent some of my early time in lockdown sketching out what such a website might look like and listing ideas for how to satisfy my self-imposed requirements. After a little thinking and a bit of research, I had a plan. Building the site My initial idea to scratch my minimalist itch was to develop a series of Python scripts that would take data from text files, format them according to some HTML templates, and publish them to my web server. Then I discovered Jekyll, which already did all of that - and it’s much better, and has many more features, than what I would have developed. What’s not to love about open source? So I downloaded it, got it running on Linux for Windows, and built the website you’re now reading. While it is a little more complicated than this makes it sound (Jekyll lets you store common elements in separate files and call them, and uses WordPress-style loops for posts, categories, and page content), the page you’re reading now is pure HTML and CSS, lovingly crafted from the ground up with the goal of staying as minimalist as possible. After running some page load tests, I think I’ve succeeded there. There are some cool features in here that I’m quite proud of. For a start, the site is responsive and looks great on mobile (the way the homepage achieves this is slightly hacky, but I’ll probably revisit that later). It also respects your preference for light or dark mode and displays the site in the appropriate colours (I use dark mode myself, so if there are light mode bugs I haven’t spotted, please let me know). Is it perfect? No. Every so often I spot a styling bug, the meta side of things could probably do with a once over, and there are definitely some messy elements to the code that I’d like to come up with more elegant solutions for in future. But in the spirit of moving fast and breaking things, the minimum viable product you see before you functions perfectly well in displaying information provided by me to you, the reader. One other area where I could be more efficient is my use of Jekyll. Being new to the whole thing, I learnt how it functions as I built the site, which is fine, but means there are probably a lot of things I would do differently now I’m more experienced. The great thing about Jekyll, however, is that because it builds static HTML pages, the output is all that matters for the most part, and poor input isn’t going to introduce any security vulnerabilities to the website because… well, there’s nothing to hack. Hosting the site Now that I had something to share with the world, I needed somewhere to share it from. A bunch of HTML pages could be hosted anywhere, and the easiest thing to do would have been to stick with my previous hosting provider. But by chance I came across a discussion about GitHub Pages - a free platform for personal and project sites - and thought it sounded like a great solution to my problem. With GitHub Pages, I could save some money while taking a bet that Microsoft-owned servers would be faster and more reliable than my previous provider’s. I could use my own domain, and the transition even gave me a security boost as my domain and my site files are now behind separate 2FA-enabled logins. Setup, I’ll admit, was a little fiddly. GitHub Pages is not terribly well documented besides some basic instructions, and it seems to take a while to propagate once you turn it on. Eventually I got there, however, and the pain of the initial configuration is likely to be worth the ease with which I can publish new blog posts and other changes - simply by committing changes to a GitHub repository. Adapting my content One slightly time-consuming task was updating all my WordPress content to fit the new Jekyll site. The Jekyll Exporter plug-in was invaluable in this, saving me a lot of time manually copying posts into markdown by exporting all my WordPress posts into a Jekyll-friendly format… mostly. The work that remained was still tedious. WordPress had automatically replaced all images in the body text of my posts with source addresses on its content delivery network, so I needed to replace them with the URLs of the images on my web server. Also, I’d been using a plug-in to highlight code on my WordPress site, so I needed to go through all my programming posts and wrap the code in the Jekyll tags that would apply the right formatting. This wasn’t a difficult task, but it was long-winded. My internet minimalism didn’t stop at the design, however. I’m also more conscious than ever that I want every page on my website to offer value to readers. This doesn’t mean the Off-Topic category is going anywhere - value isn’t limited by subject. But at some points in the past I’ve been very determined to write a blog post every two weeks, or every month, and when inspiration didn’t strike this led to some bland posts. I removed these, keeping only what I see as the higher-value posts, and I will endeavour to ensure all future posts are based around either an interesting take or useful technical content. Tracking the site So what about the elephant in the room: tracking? As I previously mentioned, some of the data provided by Google Analytics and Jetpack was useful, but it went far beyond what I needed and their use of cookies meant I needed a warning on the site to comply with EU law - something that jarred with my minimalist objective. But what else was out there? Would I need to code a tracker myself? Over a period of weeks a few different analytics start-ups flaunted their offerings on Hacker News, but they were all aimed at enterprises and priced accordingly, meaning that an analytics implementation would set me back the money I was saving on hosting (and then some). It was looking like I’d need to bite the bullet and go back to Google if I wanted any insight into which of my posts visitors enjoyed. Enter Goat Counter, which really saved the day on this. This open source analytics platform is free for personal use (although I’ll still probably buy the creators a coffee later on, once I’m sure it’s for me), and it uses a single JavaScript file to generate simple statistics: pages visited, referrers, countries, browsers, screeen size, and so on. It’s just the level of detail I need to keep improving the site, and it’s delivered with barely any tradeoff in terms of speed or user privacy. There are no cookies, either! Final thoughts All in all, this has worked out pretty well. The site loads quickly, and the process for creating a new post is both more straightforward and more flexible than it was under WordPress. It looks something like this:         1. Write post in Markdown format         2. Run Jekyll to generate HTML pages         3. Copy HTML to GitHub repository folder         4. Push update to GitHub to publish The additional benefit of no paid hosting only sweetens the deal, and means that all I need to pay for is my domain. And I don’t even need to remember to back up my website anymore, because: a) it’s stored on GitHub, a more reliable platform than my previous provider; and b) the latest HTML files generated by Jekyll will always be on my hard drive, where they will be automatically picked up by my usual backups. It’s taken a lot of work, and probably would have taken a lot longer if it wasn’t for the extra time afforded by the COVID-19 lockdown, but overall I think I can call the project a success. I now have a light, fast-loading website that respects users’ privacy and better reflects who I am. There are changes to be made and features I want to add, but the beauty of the Jekyll/GitHub setup is that I can continue to develop at my own pace and the site will still function. I’m also interested in any feedback visitors might have about the change, so if you have any thoughts, ideas, or suggestions for updates, please do use the links below to get in touch.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why virtual cyber security conferences should be the new normal</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2020/05/02/virtual-cyber-security-conferences-new-normal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why virtual cyber security conferences should be the new normal" /><published>2020-05-02T12:05:40+01:00</published><updated>2020-05-02T12:05:40+01:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2020/05/02/virtual-cyber-security-conferences-new-normal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mattcasmith.net/2020/05/02/virtual-cyber-security-conferences-new-normal/">&lt;p&gt;It’s not just TV presenters who have been broadcasting from their homes during the COVID-19 lockdown. Cyber security conferences have also gone virtual, opening them up to attendees who would otherwise be unable to benefit.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information security conferences are usually few and far between, at least in the UK. In my experience they come around now and again, generally cost an arm and a leg to attend, and mostly take a corporate perspective on things, focusing on CISO-level issues. With a few exceptions, we’re mostly talking Black Hat’s shirts and trousers rather than Def Con’s uniform of black t-shirts and shorts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of the cooler, smaller, more informal cons seem to happen over in the USA. It’s great that they exist, and I’d love to visit some of them one day, but to do so would require time off work and substantial costs for flights and hotels (even more so if they’re hosted in Las Vegas).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then came the COVID-19 pandemic and all of that changed. With group gatherings no longer allowed, these events were pushed out of the meatspace and some of them took up a new home online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My awareness of these new, free virtual cons began with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/introseccon&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;IntroSecCon&lt;/a&gt; – an event run for those starting out in cyber security that aimed to cover the basics of various technical disciplines that are usually glossed over at mainstream conferences. This struck me as a great idea and something that I wish had been running a few years ago when I joined the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was familiar with much of the technical content of IntroSecCon, but what kept me watching was the general atmosphere of the conference and the people involved. Where else, for example, would I get to watch Ming Chow – a member of the Def Con Wall of Sheep team – deliver packet analysis 101?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speaker lineup probably helped, but sitting on my bed watching the talks on the TV reminded me of August last year, when I watched some of the busier &lt;a href=&quot;https://mattcasmith.net/2019/08/26/im-back-def-con-inspired-hacking/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Def Con&lt;/a&gt; talks from my hotel room in Las Vegas, thinking about the potential of what I was learning. In fact, straight after IntroSecCon I dug out my second NIC and refreshed my memory by capturing some traffic from my home WiFi network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the lockdown isn’t over yet, and neither are the virtual conferences. One noteworthy event – Deserted Island Devops, which I wasn’t aware of until it was over – brought devops presentations to Animal Crossing: New Horizons. I didn’t realise what had happened before I saw a picture of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/chriseng/status/1255862302366216197&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;a virtual Ian Coldwater giving a talk at the front of an in-game conference hall&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up, I’m looking forward to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.magnetvirtualsummit.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Magnet Forensics’ Virtual Summit 2020&lt;/a&gt;, which essentially consists of two DFIR webinars per day across most of May. I’ve signed up for talks on memory analysis, ransomware, and email-delivered malware among other topics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s so great about this new generation of conferences is their accessibility. I don’t need to take time off work, I don’t need to travel, and in most cases I don’t need to pay a penny to learn about cyber security from some of the best minds in the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For that reason, I hope this trend continues and these events are still put on far beyond the end of the COVID-19 lockdown. That’s not to say we should move all in-person conferences online (certain types of networking only happen in person), but we could all really benefit from the educational content, digital networking opportunities, and sense of community and innovation that virtual cons foster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@cwmonty?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Chris Montgomery&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/s/photos/webcam?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unsplash&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><category term="Conferences" /><category term="Cyber Security" /><category term="Events" /><category term="Learning" /><summary type="html">It’s not just TV presenters who have been broadcasting from their homes during the COVID-19 lockdown. Cyber security conferences have also gone virtual, opening them up to attendees who would otherwise be unable to benefit.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/zoom.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/zoom.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">SANS FOR508: I’m now a GIAC Certified Forensic Analyst</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2020/03/28/sans-for508-incident-response-threat-hunting-digital-forensics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SANS FOR508: I&amp;#8217;m now a GIAC Certified Forensic Analyst" /><published>2020-03-28T09:21:41+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-28T09:21:41+00:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2020/03/28/sans-for508-incident-response-threat-hunting-digital-forensics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mattcasmith.net/2020/03/28/sans-for508-incident-response-threat-hunting-digital-forensics/">&lt;p&gt;After two and a half years in incident response it was time for another SANS course – FOR508: Advanced Incident Response, Threat Hunting, and Digital Forensics – with a tough exam I squeezed in just before COVID-19 consigned us all to our homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SANS doesn’t seem to stipulate anymore that you should take &lt;a href=&quot;https://mattcasmith.net/2017/03/27/finishing-line-ive-passed-my-gcih-exam/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;SEC504: Incident Handling and Hacker Tools and Techniques&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://mattcasmith.net/2018/10/19/sans-for500-windows-forensic-analysis/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;FOR500: Windows Forensic Analysis&lt;/a&gt; before you approach FOR508, but I would still say that’s a sensible path. I felt FOR508 acted as a nice capstone to the trio, tying together everything I’d learnt on the previous two courses and showing how to apply it to APT-level attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was the overarching theme, in my opinion. Where the introductory SANS courses taught the basics of how attacks work and how they can be detected and prevented, the examples were always fairly noisy and easy to spot. FOR508 took this to the next level, showing techniques to help incident responders and threat hunters identify activity by adversaries taking significant precautions to hide their movements in a vast enterprise environment where it’s impossible to analyse every endpoint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, this meant some additional techniques were covered. Malware (as well as the ways it can be hidden and made persistent) was examined in far greater detail. We were taught how to find and decode commands executed in PowerShell, a mainstay of modern cyber attacks. Memory forensics with Volatility formed a core – and particularly fascinating – part of the content. And the course finished with a deep dive into the inner workings of the NTFS file system, timestamp tampering, and how evidence – or even copies – of deleted files can be dragged up based on the metadata available on the disk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When all this is combined with the process-focused segments, I believe SANS FOR508 has made me a much better rounded incident responder and threat hunter. If an attacker is trying to cover their tracks with obfuscation and wiping, key evidence exists only in an endpoint’s memory, or malware is hiding like a needle in a haystack across thousands of computers and servers, I think I would have a far better chance of identifying them now and determining how far the activity had spread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, the final day of the course was devoted to a challenge giving students the chance to put everything they’d learnt into practice. We were supplied with timelines and disk and memory images from across a small enterprise network and tasked with identifying malicious activity, presenting our findings to the rest of the class at the end. I won’t give anything away here, but the exercise was a lot of fun and my team were voted the winners, giving me another SANS challenge coin for my collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GIAC exam was honestly a tough one – definitely the most challenging of the four I’ve taken so far. But that’s in keeping with the tone of the course, where the focus is as much on analysis and judgement as it is on content and knowledge. This was also the first GIAC exam I’ve taken that had a practical element – something I was slightly skeptical of given the state of the PCs in most exam centres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when it came down to it the virtual machine worked without a hitch, and I have to say I actually enjoyed having the opportunity to demonstrate my new skills when it mattered. I walked out with a score of 89 per cent and the GIAC Certified Forensic Analyst (GCFA) certification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, SANS FOR508: Advanced Incident Response, Threat Hunting, and Digital Forensics was a huge course, a massive challenge, and hugely valuable. I would recommend it to anybody working in incident response, threat hunting, or forensics who is looking to take their skills to the next level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@olloweb?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Agence Olloweb&lt;/a&gt; on&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/s/photos/magnifying-glass?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unsplash&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><category term="Cyber Security" /><category term="Forensics" /><category term="GCFA" /><category term="GIAC" /><category term="Incident Response" /><category term="Learning" /><category term="Logging" /><category term="Memory" /><category term="NTFS" /><category term="SANS" /><category term="Threat Hunting" /><category term="Windows" /><summary type="html">After two and a half years in incident response it was time for another SANS course – FOR508: Advanced Incident Response, Threat Hunting, and Digital Forensics – with a tough exam I squeezed in just before COVID-19 consigned us all to our homes.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/magnifying_glass.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/magnifying_glass.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Setting up Pi-hole to rein in an extremely noisy Samsung Smart TV</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2020/02/15/pi-hole-samsung-smart-tv/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Setting up Pi-hole to rein in an extremely noisy Samsung Smart TV" /><published>2020-02-15T12:00:34+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-15T12:00:34+00:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2020/02/15/pi-hole-samsung-smart-tv</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mattcasmith.net/2020/02/15/pi-hole-samsung-smart-tv/">&lt;p&gt;A restless mind, a new feature, and a concerning news story had me worried about privacy over Christmas. Here’s how I installed Pi-hole on my home network to try to block requests from my Samsung Smart TV – and what the data it collected revealed…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the night before Christmas – or at least some time in December – and I was browsing through the options on my Samsung Smart TV for something to watch when I noticed a Sony PlayStation advert on the main menu. That was odd, I thought. There was never a banner there before (sigh), and how would Samsung know that I play video games? They had no way of knowing which consoles I owned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/01/pihole0.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t think much of it at the time and so didn’t take a photo (the one above was taken a week or two later when the next banner appeared). PlayStation ads do appear during breaks on prime time TV, after all, so it might not have been tailored at all. I only reached the point of taking action a weeks later, when Reddit alerted me to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.privateinternetaccess.com/blog/2020/01/samsung-smart-tvs-are-set-to-upload-screenshots-of-what-youre-watching/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;a disturbing-sounding news story about Samsung Smart TVs&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Samsung’s privacy policy reveals an unnerving reality: that Samsung Smart TVs are sending clips of whatever is playing on the television to be sent back to Samsung. It’s hard to imagine a deeper violation of privacy from a smart TV set than having a screenshot of what you’re watching be uploaded to the cloud for corporate advertising purposes…&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;If you enable Samsung’s Internet-Based Advertising service, your TV viewing history will be siphoned up and sent back to Samsung to be shared with third parties that pay Samsung to send advertising directly to your screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I want to be completely clear that I cannot vouch for the source and I have absolutely no idea whether my TV was sending clips to Samsung (one of the most popular posts on this blog, in fact, was about &lt;a href=&quot;https://mattcasmith.net/2017/11/26/the-day-instagram-advertisingread-my-mind/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;eerily relevant adverts that are likely down to clever data science&lt;/a&gt;). But the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.samsung.com/us/account/privacy-policy/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;privacy policy&lt;/a&gt; concerned me, and however you look at it, retroactively embedding advertising into a product I paid hundreds of pounds for is not cool. So I set out to find a way to put an end to this behaviour…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-black-hole-for-advertisements&quot;&gt;A black hole for advertisements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;a href=&quot;https://pi-hole.net/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Pi-hole&lt;/a&gt; – an open-source software package designed to be installed on a Raspberry Pi that can be used to block connections to advertising domains. This can improve the user’s browsing privacy across all devices on the network – even within apps on smartphones and TVs – bolster network security by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sans.org/reading-room/whitepapers/hsoffice/defense-in-depth-small-office-home-office-39350&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;blocking potential callouts to malware command and control servers&lt;/a&gt;, and (in theory, at least) boost internet browsing speeds by saving endpoints the effort of downloading all those banner ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how exactly does this magic box work? Every time you try to connect to a website – let’s say you enter “example.xyz” in Firefox – your computer sends a domain name system (DNS) request asking a DNS server for the IP address corresponding to that domain. If the DNS server replies and tells your computer that example.xyz’s IP address is 1.2.3.4, your computer will then make a connection to 1.2.3.4 and ask for the data that makes up the web page you requested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pi-hole sits on your network and acts as the designated DNS server for all your devices. Your router passes all DNS requests to the Pi-hole and it checks the domains against blacklists of advertising and malware domains. If the domain is a match, the DNS request is blocked and never returned. If it checks out, the DNS request is passed to a DNS server on the internet for a response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the Pi-hole effectively prevents your computer from knowing where advertising servers are located, meaning banner ads and tracking scripts fail to load. An added benefit for data geeks like me is that it logs all this data and displays it on a neat web interface that acts as a rough approximation of a record of all browsing activity on your home network – interesting for tinkering and analysis, although the data can be anonymised and turned down for the privacy-conscious among us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/piholedash.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;setup-and-dns-log-analysis&quot;&gt;Setup and DNS log analysis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setup was… not smooth. It turned out that my provider’s cheap router (which I’m planning on replacing) doesn’t like setting changes, and more than once it went non-responsive and showed a configuration of lights that internet forums informed me meant it was bricked and would need to be replaced. Luckily they were wrong, and within a few hours I had both a functional router and a Pi-hole ready for action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took the extra measure of setting up the Pi-hole as a dynamic host configuration protocol (DHCP) server, making it responsible for handing out IP addresses to devices on my network. This way it can be set to assign static IP addresses and custom names to known devices, making it a lot easier to keep track of which device is responsible for which DNS requests in the Pi-hole’s logs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step was to find out what domains my smart TV was making requests to so I could block them. This might sound like it would require intricate detective work, but it was actually extremely easy, because once I filtered the Pi-hole logs for requests from my TV I could see that it was calling out to several domains, some of them as frequently as &lt;em&gt;every couple of seconds&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;samsungcloudsolution.com&lt;br /&gt;
samsungrm.net&lt;br /&gt;
samsungelectronics.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first of those was the main culprit, but there may be more – I’m keeping an eye on it for now and will update my settings accordingly. A quick blacklisting later and my Pi-hole was set to reject any DNS requests for these domains. It was time to switch everything back on and take a look at the results…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/01/pihole1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the graph above and guess when I turned on my Samsung Smart TV. It’s not a trick question – after blacklisting the domain names above, the percentage of the total DNS requests on my network that were blocked shot up to more than 50 per cent, including 7,000 during that football match alone!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;project-in-review&quot;&gt;Project in review&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is my TV actually doing over all these attempted connections? Is it really taking screen captures of my viewing and sending them back to Samsung for analysis? That’s a question that goes beyond the scope of my project. Even if I allowed the connection and intercepted the packets, it’s likely (hopefully) that their contents would be encrypted and unreadable, so it’s hard to say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is likely, however, that these calls out to Samsung’s servers are used for at least some kind of tracking or metrics purposes, because that’s what tech firms do (because they’re full of data geeks like myself). And I can say for certain that they’re non-essential, because since I blocked them the functionality of my smart TV hasn’t been affected at all. Funnily enough, I haven’t seen any more ads, either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So was this a slightly paranoid exercise? Maybe. But I’d been wanting to experiment with a Pi-hole for a little while, so it gave me an excuse to set one up, and helped me to both learn a little bit more about network behaviour and put what I already knew into practice. The Pi-hole is also a source of some potentially interesting logs – so perhaps look out for some analysis in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><category term="Cyber Security" /><category term="Data" /><category term="Linux" /><category term="Log Analysis" /><category term="Logging" /><category term="Networking" /><category term="Pi-hole" /><category term="Privacy" /><category term="Raspberry Pi" /><category term="Samsung" /><category term="TV" /><category term="Web Browsing" /><summary type="html">A restless mind, a new feature, and a concerning news story had me worried about privacy over Christmas. Here’s how I installed Pi-hole on my home network to try to block requests from my Samsung Smart TV – and what the data it collected revealed…</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/01/pihole.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/01/pihole.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Long-form – HTTPS and VPNs: How private is your internet browsing?</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2020/02/02/https-vpns-private-internet-browsing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Long-form &amp;#8211; HTTPS and VPNs: How private is your internet browsing?" /><published>2020-02-02T12:49:59+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-02T12:49:59+00:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2020/02/02/https-vpns-private-internet-browsing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mattcasmith.net/2020/02/02/https-vpns-private-internet-browsing/">&lt;p&gt;Web browsing privacy is of increasing concern as people’s business and personal lives become ever more entwined with the internet. This essay examines various connection scenarios to establish how secure your data really is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After years of industry concern, web browsing privacy is finally becoming a matter of interest to the public. There may be several factors behind this, including the Edward Snowden leaks, which revealed the extent to which western governments monitor their citizens’ online activity, and various headline-grabbing data leaks. Although these do not exactly align to web browsing for the most part, there is no doubt they have increased awareness of cyber security and privacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Virtual private network (VPN) providers have been quick to capitalise on this, and have entered the public eye so emphatically that NordVPN was even unveiled as the “official cyber security partner” of 2019 Premier League runners-up Liverpool FC. It is not uncommon in the United Kingdom to see dramatic television adverts that imply that hackers can own users instantly if they are not using a VPN. But what exactly does a VPN hide? And how private is your browsing otherwise?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This essay will explore web browsing privacy for users utilising various combinations of a range of technologies, including HTTPS-encrypted connections and VPNs. For each scenario, I will consider what a user’s internet service provider (ISP) and VPN provider can see, as well as the owners of the websites visited and any malicious actors monitoring traffic crossing the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;assumptions&quot;&gt;Assumptions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to focus on the issue of web browsing privacy, it is necessary to make a few assumptions about our theoretical hosts sending and receiving the internet traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, I will assume that the user’s endpoint is not compromised. If a malicious actor has successfully installed malware on a user’s machine, no number of network protections will ensure their privacy. The hacker may be able to record the user’s keystrokes, record which URLs they visit, take screenshots, and retrieve files, usernames, passwords, and other data from the computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also assume that the various service providers involved have not been compromised. If a cyber criminal has “owned” the user’s ISP or VPN provider then they would be able to access all the data visible to those organisations. This essay will detail what data those corporations can see – just assume that if they were compromised then the attackers would see the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, there’s the matter of the website the user is browsing to, which again I will assume is secure. There are several factors at play here, including the webmaster’s backend security and the user’s choice of password and/or multi-factor authentication if it is a web service with an account. It is safe to say that if the website is compromised then the user’s browsing activity and any data sent to the site (e.g. information entered in forms) will be visible to the attacker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;http-browsing&quot;&gt;HTTP browsing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until recent years, the internet was solely reliant on the HyperText Transfer Protocol (HTTP). While most websites have now switched to the encrypted version – HyperText Transfer Protocol Secure (HTTPS) – some less vigilant webmasters are still serving pages via HTTP. The issue here is that as HTTP is not encrypted, anybody in the middle can see all the browsing data, which is why most modern web browsers flag HTTP connections with a warning message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/http_v2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means the ISP can see exactly which page was requested by the user, as well as any additional information they enter – for instance via forms. While it is unlikely that an ISP will actively monitor this data (at least in the UK), HTTP also leaves it open to other observers on its route to the web server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real concern here is that any attacker sniffing traffic (i.e. collecting and reading the packets of data sent over the network) can also see everything. This raises privacy concerns if, for example, they can see what Google searches were made or which Facebook profiles were visited, but it can also be disastrous for security – as the attacker can see all data sent over HTTP, this means they can collect any usernames and passwords entered and use them to access or hijack the user’s accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, HTTP should be avoided at all costs. Luckily, in 2020 nearly all mainstream websites and apps used in the western world – Google, Facebook, Twitter, and Instagram, for example – have moved to HTTPS, which encrypts web traffic. Those that have not (and they are surprisingly common outside of the English language internet, at least based on my experience) should be avoided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;https-browsing&quot;&gt;HTTPS browsing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what happens if the user accesses a site over HTTPS? In this case, Transport Layer Security (TLS) is used to encrypt the data sent and received to shield it from prying eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new TLS connection is made with each website the user browses to over HTTPS. When the user’s computer contacts the server, they exchange “hello” messages containing random data. The computer verifies the server’s Secure Socket Layer (SSL) certificate is legitimate and the client sends a premaster secret, encrypted with the public key from the server’s SSL certificate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The server decrypts the premaster secret using its private key, and both systems generate session keys using the client/server random data and premaster secret. Then both systems send “ready” messages encrypted with this session key, signifying that the handshake is complete and the encrypted connection is ready for use. All data sent from this point is encrypted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/https_v2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does that encrypted connection mean for browsing privacy? All data sent between the client and the server is encrypted, meaning it cannot be understood by the user’s ISP or anybody eavesdropping on network traffic. However, it is worth noting that the initial Domain Name Service (DNS) request, which looks up the IP address that corresponds to a domain, will still be in plain text, so the domain visited (e.g. MattCASmith.net) can be picked out and used to track browsing activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To combat this, a new system called DNS over HTTPS is being tested. However, this will not necessarily completely hide the site the user is visiting – it will just make it slightly more difficult to decipher. While the domain name in the DNS request will be encrypted and unreadable, third parties monitoring the site content packets sent and received will still be able to see the source and destination IP addresses on each – namely the user’s host and the web server. From there, a reverse DNS lookup can be performed on the server’s IP address to find the associated domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with HTTPS the ISP and anybody listening can see the domain requested but none of the content… and that’s about it. As always, the website itself can see all requests and submissions made to it, but it is clear that HTTPS is a massive step up from HTTP in terms of privacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vpn-browsing&quot;&gt;VPN browsing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we will take a look at what happens when the user connects via a virtual private network (VPN).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the services we discussed earlier, often marketed with vague promises about encryption and security. But what exactly do they do? Essentially, a VPN creates an encrypted tunnel between the user’s computer and the VPN provider’s server. This means all data transmitted between those two points – including DNS requests and content sent over HTTP – is encrypted and cannot be read by the user’s ISP or anybody sniffing packets from the network between these two points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As connections are made via the VPN server, this also masks the user’s IP address and location from the destination website. This is how some people use VPNs to access Netflix content intended for other nations – if the VPN server is in the Netherlands, for example, then Netflix’s server sees a viewer browsing from that server’s Dutch IP address and returns Dutch content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/vpn_v2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a VPN still has its limitations and does not provide bulletproof privacy. As always, the website visited will know which pages were requested and can store any information the user enters. Even though it can only see the VPN server’s IP address, the site will know who the user is if they log in or have cookies stored on their computer from previous visits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also worth noting that the protocol used for the final leg of the route – between the VPN server and the web server – depends on whether the web server supports HTTPS. If it does not, this connection will be over HTTP and the usual warnings about packet sniffing apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the biggest risk with a VPN lies with the VPN provider itself. By using a VPN, a user is essentially transferring their trust from their ISP to the VPN provider, as all of their browsing data passes through its servers. If the VPN provider is untrustworthy or has been breached, then malicious actors could potentially see everything that the user does online (potentially even data sent and received from web servers over HTTPS with a successful man in the middle attack).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logging is also a consideration. While many VPN providers claim not to keep logs of their users’ browsing activity, it is not always wise to take their word for it, as some users have previously discovered. Not only do some VPN providers – especially the free ones – stand to profit from selling such data to advertisers, they may also be required to hand them over to law enforcement if requested, depending on the country the data is stored in. Be sure to do your research before signing up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-keep-your-web-browsing-private&quot;&gt;How to keep your web browsing private&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s the best approach for users who want to avoid revealing their browsing habits to the world? Browsing over HTTP is certainly a no-no, but there are pros and cons to be weighed up when it comes to choosing between a VPN and good old-fashioned HTTPS (which should still be used wherever possible).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HTTPS encrypts all web content, and while the DNS request domain will be visible, that probably will not be of much concern for the average user as “google.com” or “bbc.co.uk” does not give away much about their activity. However, while the bulk of mainstream sites are up-to-date, some websites still use HTTP connections, which do not offer the same privacy and may pose a potential risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A VPN, on the other hand, encrypts all data between the user’s computer and the VPN server, even when communicating with sites over HTTP. However, the user essentially entrusts all of their data to the VPN provider, and choosing a trustworthy one can be tricky. A bad choice (or a successful attack on the provider) could spill all of their secrets to an attacker or law enforcement agency anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And again, it is worth underlining here that none of these technologies protect data sent to a website. The web server will always know which pages the user browsed to and what data they submitted. If a VPN is used then this activity will be logged against the VPN server’s IP address, but at the end of the day user data is at the mercy of the site’s privacy policies and security defences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all likelihood, taking basic security precautions and sticking to websites that support HTTPS should provide enough privacy for the typical user. However, if you are likely to be using HTTP (or are simply uncomfortable with your ISP knowing which domains you visit) then a VPN can provide an extra layer of privacy – just make sure you choose one that you can trust. As with many choices in cyber security, it all comes down to your personal risk profile and how much you’re willing to spend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pexels.com/@junior-teixeira-1064069?utm_content=attributionCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=pexels&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Junior Teixeira&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pexels.com/photo/semi-opened-laptop-computer-turned-on-on-table-2047905/?utm_content=attributionCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=pexels&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Pexels&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><category term="Cyber Security" /><category term="Encryption" /><category term="HTTPS" /><category term="Privacy" /><category term="VPN" /><category term="Web Browsing" /><summary type="html">Web browsing privacy is of increasing concern as people’s business and personal lives become ever more entwined with the internet. This essay examines various connection scenarios to establish how secure your data really is.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/privacy.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/privacy.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A slightly geeky trip to Edinburgh: Castles, museums, and Star Wars</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2019/12/20/edinburgh-castle-museum-star-wars/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A slightly geeky trip to Edinburgh: Castles, museums, and Star Wars" /><published>2019-12-20T13:00:29+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-20T13:00:29+00:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2019/12/20/edinburgh-castle-museum-star-wars</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mattcasmith.net/2019/12/20/edinburgh-castle-museum-star-wars/">&lt;p&gt;My Christmas break has officially begun! With an excess of leave to use after &lt;a href=&quot;https://mattcasmith.net/2019/11/30/update-cyber-security-projects-another-trip-to-japan-and-plans-for-2020/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;all this year’s hard work&lt;/a&gt;, I kicked off the festive season with a trip to Edinburgh, where I hit the usual tourist traps, found some geeky gems, and tried to avoid freezing.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-usual-suspects&quot;&gt;The usual suspects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some things that are must-dos whenever you visit a major city. In Edinburgh’s case the obvious candidate was the castle, which provided an interesting glimpse into the past and a surprising amount of modern history, too. This was also where I tried the first (sort-of) whisky that I’ve ever properly liked – a locally-produced liqueur made with fermented honey. So it gets credit for that, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/edinburghstripa.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also visited the pretty little Dean Village, which was crawling with Instagrammers, before taking a surprisingly quiet stroll up the Water of Leith and under the Dean Bridge to Stockbridge, where I stopped at a cosy French patisserie called Madeleine for a quiche and hot chocolate. In the evenings I also ended up making a couple of stops at a place called The Pop-Up Geeks, which at the time of my visit was decked out as the Star Wars Cantina and serving drinks inspired by the space saga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My impression based on my couple of days of wandering is that Edinburgh is a picturesque city with a lot of history, and outside of the obvious spots – Edinburgh Castle and the Christmas market, for example – it was largely free of the hordes of tourists that Londoners are forced to endure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;national-museum-of-scotland&quot;&gt;National Museum of Scotland&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gets a section all of its own because it was the highlight of my trip. The National Museum of Scotland sits slightly to the south of the Royal Mile in a beautiful building full of open spaces occupied by suspended animals and – to my surprise – planes. You could easily spend an entire day exploring the museum’s collections, but I made the most of the couple of hours I had and it was well worth the visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/edinburghstripb.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The technology hall, which houses the famous cloned sheep Dolly, also had a rack of Formula 1 cars that charted the development of the former Stewart team (Jos Verstappen) through its Jaguar years (Eddie Irvine) to the Red Bull of today. My only complaint was that as the cars were stacked on top of each other it wasn’t possible to get a close look at any of them but David Coulthard’s Red Bull.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, though, I have to say the National Museum of Scotland’s presentation was impeccable throughout. The halls at either end of the building were the highlights, but the other exhibitions – including one on Asian history that featured a few Japanese pieces – were just as well done on a smaller scale. The museum didn’t feature prominently on the lists of attractions I reviewed prior to my trip, but I’d certainly make time for a longer visit if I ever return to Scotland in future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><category term="Aviation" /><category term="Design" /><category term="Edinburgh" /><category term="Engineering" /><category term="Food" /><category term="Formula 1" /><category term="Lifestyle" /><category term="Museums" /><category term="Racing" /><category term="Science" /><category term="Scotland" /><category term="Travel" /><category term="Walking" /><summary type="html">My Christmas break has officially begun! With an excess of leave to use after all this year’s hard work, I kicked off the festive season with a trip to Edinburgh, where I hit the usual tourist traps, found some geeky gems, and tried to avoid freezing.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/edinburghmain.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/edinburghmain.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Update: Cyber security projects, another trip to Japan, and plans for 2020</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2019/11/30/update-cyber-security-projects-another-trip-to-japan-and-plans-for-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Update: Cyber security projects, another trip to Japan, and plans for 2020" /><published>2019-11-30T18:59:45+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-30T18:59:45+00:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2019/11/30/update-cyber-security-projects-another-trip-to-japan-and-plans-for-2020</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mattcasmith.net/2019/11/30/update-cyber-security-projects-another-trip-to-japan-and-plans-for-2020/">&lt;p&gt;It’s been a while… again. Time for another update about what I’ve been up to both professionally and personally and an outline of my plans for 2020, when I’ll be taking a step up in terms of personal projects in my free time.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-to-work&quot;&gt;Getting to work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mattcasmith.net/2019/08/26/im-back-def-con-inspired-hacking/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;My refreshed post-Las Vegas feeling&lt;/a&gt; didn’t last long, as it was soon time to get back into the swing of things in the office. Luckily, since the middle of the year I’ve been working on something quite interesting – for the first time ever, I’ve been leading my own project. This has involved managing a small team and a budget and working across nearly the full breadth of services provided by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://mattcasmith.net/2018/06/01/what-a-security-operations-centre-soc-is-and-how-it-works/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;security operations centre (SOC)&lt;/a&gt;, drawing on nearly everything I’ve learnt up to this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For obvious reasons I can’t go into too much detail here, but the content has been very interesting and it’s been incredibly satisfying to be given the autonomy to see a project through from design to completion. I still have some deadlines to meet for this year, but my next step in the new year is likely going to involve managing a slightly bigger project in a different area (one I’m keen to learn about), so I’m quite excited to take on more responsibility, even if it does mean a little more work and stress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rest-and-relaxation&quot;&gt;Rest and relaxation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all this going on it was no wonder I felt a bit burnt out by October. With the exception of a long weekend for the British Grand Prix I’d had no leave in 2019, so I was approaching a zombie-like state by the time I got to jet off to Japan for a two-week holiday that included the Japanese Grand Prix and an excursion to the island of Okinawa. I had a more relaxed few days off in November and have a long Christmas break to look forward to – even if I do have more deadlines to meet before then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/11/japan_gp.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Japan was great (&lt;a href=&quot;https://mattcasmith.net/2018/03/17/here-are-some-of-the-best-things-i-did-saw-and-ate-in-japan/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;once again&lt;/a&gt;). I explored the local video game shops, visited the world’s biggest planetarium, ate some amazing izakaya food, sheltered from a typhoon, saw some Formula 1, and stretched out on the beach at the end. During my time off in the UK in November, I visted family and had the chance to indulge in some video games for the first time in a while – &lt;em&gt;Red Dead Redemption 2&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Skyrim Special Edition&lt;/em&gt;, and Hideo Kojima’s new game &lt;em&gt;Death Stranding&lt;/em&gt; were all on the agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That time off gave me a chance to relax (at least when I wasn’t cramming myself into the Nagoya subway) and think about what I want to achieve in my free time. It was obvious that it wasn’t sustainable to spend eight or more hours in the office each day and then head home to watch videos on LinkedIn Learning. That kind of learning was too passive, and if I was tired after my day at the office the information would kind of pass over me anyway. So I brainstormed new ideas for 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-years-resolutions&quot;&gt;New year’s resolutions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some thought, I narrowed my ambitions down to three objectives for the new year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Design and code a video game&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As fun as &lt;a href=&quot;https://mattcasmith.net/tag/raspberry-pi-home-hub&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;my Raspberry Pi Home Hub project&lt;/a&gt; was, once I’d got all the components working on one screen I was essentially repeating the process for them all, and the code’s reliance on external resources meant that whenever a site changed its RSS feed format I’d have to update the Python that parsed it. It all got a bit tiresome. Next year I want to try something new – I want to make a simple video game using the PyGame library. I have some initial ideas, but I’ll write more about it once I get going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Write cyber security essays&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Secondly, I still want to further my cyber security knowledge, but in a more active way than watching videos. I was reading an article in the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sans.org/reading-room&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;SANS Reading Room&lt;/a&gt; when I had an idea: as I encounter security questions I don’t have the answers to, I’ll research them and write up a few thousand words as an essay or paper to make sure I’m processing the information and it sinks in. I may complete one every month or two, depending on time. If they’re good, I might even share them here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Engage with the cyber security community&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
My third resolution in terms of tech and security in 2020 is to get more involved in the community. In the past few months I’ve attended a student event or two but I’d like to do more and hang out with some other professionals, too. This might be a bit difficult as my job regularly involves travel, but I’m going to be on the lookout for cyber security events and will make an effort to blog about what I find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also finally have a laptop that works (I tried every solution on the internet for the mysterious issue of Windows 10 maxing out the disk I/O all the time – it turned out it may have been a hardware fault as a new hard drive fixed it) so I’m a lot more mobile and can work from hotels and coffee shops. It’s plastered in stickers I picked up at &lt;a href=&quot;https://mattcasmith.net/2019/08/26/im-back-def-con-inspired-hacking/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Black Hat and Def Con&lt;/a&gt; so at this point it’s officially a hacker laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I dusted off this website (I know that &lt;a href=&quot;https://mattcasmith.net/2019/08/26/im-back-def-con-inspired-hacking/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;back in August&lt;/a&gt; I promised I was back, but I hadn’t logged on for a while and had some SSL and PHP issues – oops) and got writing. I still haven’t forgotten the sense of community I felt in Las Vegas and my inbox is still open to anyone who wants to chat – whether you’re a student with questions about the cyber security industry or a veteran with some feedback to share, please leave a comment below and I’ll get back to you as soon as time allows!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><category term="Business" /><category term="Corporate IT" /><category term="Cyber Security" /><category term="Design" /><category term="Development" /><category term="IT" /><category term="Japan" /><category term="Learning" /><category term="Lifestyle" /><category term="Management" /><category term="Project Management" /><category term="Python" /><category term="SANS" /><category term="SOC" /><category term="Video Games" /><category term="Websites" /><summary type="html">It’s been a while… again. Time for another update about what I’ve been up to both professionally and personally and an outline of my plans for 2020, when I’ll be taking a step up in terms of personal projects in my free time.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2019/11/laptop.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2019/11/laptop.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Update: I’m back, and Def Con has inspired me to get hacking</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2019/08/26/im-back-def-con-inspired-hacking/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Update: I&amp;#8217;m back, and Def Con has inspired me to get hacking" /><published>2019-08-26T17:18:53+01:00</published><updated>2019-08-26T17:18:53+01:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2019/08/26/im-back-def-con-inspired-hacking</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mattcasmith.net/2019/08/26/im-back-def-con-inspired-hacking/">&lt;p&gt;Hi – it’s been a while! When I checked my blog I was surprised to see I hadn’t posted in a whole four months, since April. The good news is that I’m back, and I’m more inspired than I have been in a long time to get learning, designing, and programming.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;back-to-blogging&quot;&gt;Back to blogging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began the year with good intentions, but by making a resolution to blog each week I inadvertently made blogging a chore (I realised this while reading Daniel H. Pink’s book &lt;em&gt;Drive&lt;/em&gt;, which details what he calls “Motivation 3.0”). This – along with work, personal stuff, and other projects – was the reason my usually regular posts dropped off, but I’m going to make an effort to keep my blog alive from now on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Posts will no longer be weekly, but I will be writing as and when I have something interesting to say, exciting news to share, or a neat project to show off. I think the quality will increase this way, anyway, as there were times before when I needed to write something according to my weekly schedule but was scrambling around for ideas that might not have warranted their own posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;back-to-tech&quot;&gt;Back to tech&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through a series of extremely fortunate events, I also got to do something amazing a few weeks ago: my company flew me out to Las Vegas for Hacker Summer Camp 2019 – otherwise known as Black Hat USA 2019 and Def Con 27. I’m extremely grateful to have had the chance to go. I saw some awesome things, met some fun people, and can say I’ve been to Vegas and explored the Strip (even if I wouldn’t necessarily choose to go back for a holiday any time soon).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Black Hat was interesting, Def Con was inspirational. Spread across four different hotels, the event consisted of a main conference and separate rooms dotted around for just about every niche you could think of: red team, blue team, the internet of things, packet analysis, social engineering, and more. I didn’t have a laptop with me to get involved with the practical events, but this gave me the advantage of being able to wander and take everything in. It really opened my eyes to areas I hadn’t even considered before, and reminded me of why I wanted to get into cyber security to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;back-to-learning&quot;&gt;Back to learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this has given me a lot to think about since I’ve come back to London. In my couple of weeks back on British soil I’ve already dipped back into Python to fix some bugs with &lt;a href=&quot;https://mattcasmith.net/tag/raspberry-pi-home-hub&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;my Raspberry Pi Home Hub&lt;/a&gt; (shout out to the BBC for removing the images from their RSS feeds and screwing things up) and taken an online course covering the basics of electronics, which has given me some great ideas for some potential future Arduino-based projects that I might get cracking on in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So please do keep coming back and keep an eye out for new posts and projects! As well as inspiring me to be more active in my free time, my trip has reminded me of the amazing community around cyber security and hacking, and I’d love to hear from people and swap ideas and advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@daniilvnoutchkov?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Daniil Vnoutchkov&lt;/a&gt; on&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/search/photos/las-vegas?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unsplash&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><category term="Cyber Security" /><category term="Def Con" /><category term="Design" /><category term="Development" /><category term="Electronics" /><category term="Events" /><category term="Las Vegas" /><category term="Learning" /><category term="Lifestyle" /><category term="Python" /><category term="Raspberry Pi" /><category term="Travel" /><category term="USA" /><summary type="html">Hi – it’s been a while! When I checked my blog I was surprised to see I hadn’t posted in a whole four months, since April. The good news is that I’m back, and I’m more inspired than I have been in a long time to get learning, designing, and programming.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2019/08/vegas-2.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2019/08/vegas-2.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>