<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-05-31T10:58:41+01:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/feed.xml</id><title type="html">MattCASmith</title><subtitle>A blog about cyber security and technology</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Quality products begin with detail-obsessed leaders</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2025/05/31/abstraction-quality-detail-obsessed-leaders" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quality products begin with detail-obsessed leaders" /><published>2025-05-31T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-05-31T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2025/05/31/abstraction-quality-detail-obsessed-leaders</id><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><summary type="html">It often feels like modern business is stuck in a loop. An idea is successful, there is a push to scale it as far and quickly as possible, and it’s optimised to within an inch of its life - but normally only in the name of profit. Usually this results in a lower quality product, less satisfied customers, and a world where it seems like we’re all being squeezed for every possible penny. But is there a better way? I’ve been thinking a lot about the relationship between abstraction and quality this week. Because there are businesses out there that employ thousands, reach millions, and deliver high-quality, boundary-pushing products and services. What are they doing differently? It's crucial to maintain visibility of realities on the ground, where quality thrives or dies Once an organisation reaches a certain scale, it’s impossible for leadership to maintain visibility of what’s going on everywhere, so there’s an entire science centred around designing and collecting all sorts of metrics. But metrics are only indicators of what’s really happening. They provide an abstract view. For that reason, metrics don’t always reflect the reality on the ground. For example, a metric for the number of widgets made this week misses all sorts of context. Were they manufactured to a good quality? How long did each take?1 Were employees working at a pace that allows for attention to detail and protects their wellbeing, or were they working unsustainably quickly? Scale and agencyIt might warrant a separate post at a later date, but I think we're seeing a similar abstraction effect in wider society. National and global issues will always gain the most traction online because algorithms reward broad appeal and interaction. Just as in business, this can blind us to the details at a local level because they don't enjoy the same visibility. Frustratingly, we have greater personal agency to take action to address local matters, and they often have a more direct impact on our day-to-day lives. The financial skew Metrics commonly shared with a company’s senior leadership are also often disproportionately money-centric. Over time, this can degrade the quality of the product or service, because decisions are made for financial optimisation. If developer interviews are to be believed, one such example can be seen in Electronic Arts’ recent release of Dragon Age: The Veilguard, a disappointing chapter in a series that began in 2009 and spans four games. Each iteration further watered down the original formula in search of a larger audience and more sales, as former lead writer David Gaider explained to GamesRadar: “The nerds were in the cave. You made an RPG and the nerds in the cave would always show up for an RPG, because it was an RPG… You didn’t have to try and appeal to them. You had to worry about the people who weren’t in the cave, which was the audience we actually wanted, which was much larger.” EA’s leadership zoomed out too far, prioritising reach over the game design existing fans enjoyed. To make more revenue, the product needed to leave its niche and appeal to a broader audience. And in trying to widen its appeal, the quality of the product was degraded to a point where it attracted just 1.5 million players in two months - only half of what was expected, and paling in comparison to its 2014 predecessor Inquisition’s 12 million lifetime sales.2 This isn’t an isolated case. You encounter financial optimisation at the cost of quality (affectionately known as enshittification) on a daily basis. It’s in the chocolate bar that’s become smaller and noticeably less tasty. The customer service line with a long wait time because there are too few agents. And the previously amazing website that has injected too many ads to be usable. Detail obsession at scale But businesses are generally only getting larger. Even successful small businesses are commonly absorbed by larger conglomerates. So what does this mean for large organisations and their leaders? Are they doomed to failure once their departments become too big to maintain total oversight? I don’t think so - scale doesn’t have to mean detachment. In fact, many of the most admired business leaders and creatives in history are famous for being obsessive about detail, even when their organisations were utilising massive teams to craft products that would sell in the millions: Steve Jobs was known for his close oversight of Apple’s product design, to the point where he demanded that the original Macintosh’s internals were laid out beautifully - not just the exterior case In his work with SpaceX, Elon Musk applies a “first principles” approach, asking engineers to challenge their assumptions and requirements and often finding unorthodox solutions to problems his teams face Since founding his own studio, famously cinematic video game creator Hideo Kojima3 has personally edited every trailer for the Death Stranding games, meticulously choosing everything from shots to soundtracks The computer components, rocket engine skirts, and game trailers aren’t important here - and yet they are. These are business leaders who could have been detached from their output, monitoring financials and tracking project progress through dashboards and meetings - but instead they’re on the ground, directly influencing the most important details of their products. Businesses can still produce useful, beautiful things that push boundaries and make our world a better place, but the quality of the organisation’s output - and its long-term sustainability - depends on the willingness of those at the top to resist abstraction and stay close to the work. Notes and references You might assume you could divide the number of widgets made by the number of hours in a week for an average, but without more granular tracking you’d still severely underestimate production time if employees were working overtime to crank them out on schedule. Note the distinction between players and sales here. In my opinion, “players” is a rather deceptive metric because it’s unclear what exactly constitutes a player. Does somebody who downloaded the game on Game Pass and played it for 15 minutes count? I’m fascinated with the man and his creative process. This week I read his interview with Edge magazine, and now I’m on the edge of my seat for the release of Death Stranding 2: On the Beach next month.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/abstraction_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/abstraction_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Bluesky’s nearly there, but it won’t replace X just yet</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2025/05/24/bluesky-x-comparison" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bluesky's nearly there, but it won't replace X just yet" /><published>2025-05-24T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-05-24T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2025/05/24/bluesky-x-comparison</id><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><summary type="html">Bluesky was an indirect product of Elon Musk’s controversial 2022 Twitter takeover, pitched as a decentralised, user-first alternative to the site that became X. Originally a side project funded by Twitter itself, its new goal is to stand on its own two feet as a more open, interoperable social network. Artist's conception of the beautiful social media garden Bluesky's creators aim for There are a few reasons some users are dissatisfied with X - algorithm tweaks and moderation choices to name just a couple. Bluesky offers a kind of reset for those seeking something more akin to the Twitter of old, albeit with some modern tweaks and that underlying decentralised philosophy. But ideals aside, I was curious as to what the day-to-day Bluesky experience actually feels like. So over the course of a month, I gave it a good go. Getting started Setup was what you’d expect from any social network: an email/password signup (Bluesky currently offers multi-factor authentication only via email) followed by an opportunity to fill out some basic profile information and select your interests so the algorithm has at least something to go on. By default, I was assigned a .bsky.social username. But by confirming my domain ownership via a TXT DNS record, I was able to update it to @mattcasmith.net. This exists in the spirit of the open, platform-agnostic philosophy behind Bluesky, of course, but for me it was just a nice extra layer of personalisation to use my web address as my handle. Next came the daunting task of attempting to port my follows from X and fill my feed with interesting stuff. This process triggered some reflection on the current state of my X account. Most posts I see there come from a minority of accounts I follow, and in reviewing the list I found many silent or low-quality profiles that weren’t worth looking up on Bluesky. Maybe a clearout is due. During this process, I found the Bluesky search function to be less friendly than X’s - it seemed to rely much more on exact matches to my queries. But I also faced four more significant obstacles in recreating my X experience: Many people I follow on X were absent altogether Of those who were present, many had just parked their usernames without ever posting anything to Bluesky Many were active on Bluesky months ago, but looked like they’d abandoned their profiles and gone back to X For those posting on both social networks, many appeared to be on X more frequently and didn’t mirror everything to Bluesky These problems don’t seem to be unique to me, because during my time with Bluesky I stumbled across several bot accounts that simply reposted anything a high profile account posted to X - for example, @paulgbot. Ultimately, a social network thrives or dies based on its adoption levels within an individual user’s network, but I persevered in the name of science. Who knew, maybe I would discover hundreds of new and interesting people who I never followed on X, or who were never there in the first place. Feed and content My first impression was that the Bluesky feed looked much the same as X - perhaps even a little bit cleaner in terms of layout - but felt more responsive. It was noticeably quicker to load and refresh - although from an engineering standpoint I’m aware it’s operating at a fraction of the scale. However, there were a couple of small comparative annoyances: There’s no setting to collapse images and link previews, so it takes a lot more scrolling for me to see the same number of posts I see a fair few Japanese posts in my feeds, so it’s frustrating that that Translate link is outbound to Google Translate, adding tab clutter and requiring you to dismiss a cookie pop-up if you run a clean browser Roughly equivalent, but notice the greater information density I can achieve with X's settings From a content perspective, my first issue was that by joining Bluesky I lost all of my muted terms from X, so my Discover feed was polluted with a lot of negativity and I needed to start over to filter it out. However, with careful application of likes and mutes, its quality slowly increased. I could at least appreciate that most of the posts in my Bluesky feed originated from real people. The modern X algorithm seems to favour faceless content farm accounts in the For You feed, while Bluesky’s Discover feed primarily featured individuals and felt more genuine as a result. But Bluesky also retains the catastrophising, snarkiness, and sub-tweeting (sub-posting?) that was largely pushed out of X in recent years. It often feels like a huge competition to see who can invent the biggest grievance with the most mundane aspect of everyday life. This is perhaps best illustrated by a post I spotted from the always-brilliant Captain Disillusion: At Bluesky restaurant with friend ME: Happy birthday, dude. Stranger in next booth whips around STRANGER: Birthday?? People are dyinggg!!! I sympathise with many of the causes, but it’s exhausting as a social media experience - especially when many of the complaints interpret the original post on the least charitable terms possible. My heavily curated X feed, on the other hand, leans towards people with curiosity, optimism, and ambition. Interaction and discoverability I observed all of the above negativity in others’ discussions and stayed well out of it, but what about people’s interactions with me? Well, generally when I did jump into discussions they were pleasant. I even had one guy react positively to a counterpoint, which is basically unheard of online. I'm impressed - I've never seen such a graceful response to a dissenting opinion online But I’ll say straight up that joining Bluesky is not a cure if you’re suffering from low engagement on X. I did get a couple of likes on my first post (I’m not sure how those users found it, outside of new account promotion or the popularity of the term “AI”), but what followed was a familiar quiet. I did receive more random likes on Bluesky than I do on X, but overall I think that X feels less like yelling into a void because of its transparency on post impression metrics. On Bluesky, you have no idea whether anybody saw your post at all unless they decide to interact with it, which is much rarer. My account amassed followers more quickly than on X (just over 20 in a month, which many will consider rookie numbers), but a fair few of those were bots with OnlyFans links in their bios. What was weird is that they would often disappear from my Notifications page, so Bluesky seemed to be aware that they were spam or low-quality accounts, but my follower count never decreased accordingly, so it seems like they continued to exist. An unproven quantity What Bluesky has going for it is that some people are ideologically driven enough to keep it alive. I don’t think that getting bored will be a strong enough reason for many of its users to hop back to X, and that means that even if it’s a slow burn, ongoing use and development seems certain. And outside of the small inconveniences I mentioned, the platform mostly does a good job - it’s the network that’s currently lacking. It’s not just the tone of some of the discourse, it’s that there are simply fewer of the people I want to follow - the technologists, builders, developers, and entrepreneurs - than there are on the site formerly known as Twitter. Therefore, I would say that Bluesky is inferior to X in its current state. But that’s not to say that it’s not worth the effort. The two sites offer different experiences, and it would only take a little more momentum and a few more migrants in my niche to make it my primary social network. Until such a day, Bluesky sits in limbo. It’s enjoyable enough to continue using, but too incomplete to fulfil its goal of replacing X entirely.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/bluesky_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/bluesky_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">When you travel, the real journey isn’t photographed</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2025/05/10/travel-tourism-photos-experience" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When you travel, the real journey isn't photographed" /><published>2025-05-10T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-05-10T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2025/05/10/travel-tourism-photos-experience</id><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><summary type="html">Last week, I played tour guide for some visitors from overseas - first in London, and then in my hometown. It was exhausting, but it came with an unexpected side effect: it made me see those places differently. It’s hard to take your city for granted when you walk familiar streets with somebody seeing them for the first time. It snaps you out of your tunnel vision. But while it opened my eyes to details I usually overlook, visiting the hotspots also made me realise how hollow most modern travel really is. A view of a hotel in my hometown that dates back to 1830 - far from the London crowds My most memorable trips tend to leave a lasting impression because they offer a glimpse of life in a different place. That usually happens when I visit friends in their home countries. The highlights are rarely the popular sights, but parts of the local lifestyle that I want to adopt and bring home with me. Even when I don’t know anybody in town and spend more time on the beaten track, my takeaways often come from small details - the story behind an unusual item on a restaurant menu, or a museum exhibit that makes me think about how people used to live and the way the city evolved. That kind of encounter demands real engagement with a place - you learn something about the world, and it changes you. But city breaks increasingly seem like a checklist - the top ten Trip Advisor attractions, each dutifully photographed like digital collectables in an open-world video game. Beyond the photos and landmarks, it’s easy to miss the soul of a place entirely. That’s why parts of my London tour felt so disheartening. My guests got a small taste of London life, with some personal recommendations and home-cooked meals, but it’s hard to imagine anybody zig-zagging between tourist spots to compile their end-of-trip Instagram carousel ever would. And when the photo matters more than the moment, etiquette goes out the window. The city becomes a mere backdrop, in front of which dense crowds jostle for their 20 seconds posing against the railings. Nothing is really absorbed. Why bother, when everything’s already captured on disk? Photo opOne couple took things to a new extreme at Tower Bridge. I was standing next to a tree, waiting for my group to take in the view, when I noticed a woman about a metre away pointing her smartphone straight at me. I turned to see what she was aiming at, and realised her partner had quietly slipped in behind me to pose against the tree. Not a word was said - they simply assumed I would step aside. For a moment, I felt more like a member of staff at an amusement park than a citizen in my own city. Sadly, this outlook on travel also seems to be influencing the way our cities are being shaped. The classic London landmarks (the Houses of Parliament, the Tower of London, St. Paul’s Cathedral, and so on) were all primarily built for function - albeit with a healthy layer of beauty on top. It was coincidental that their history and aesthetics makes them worth visiting so much later. Most attractions built since the turn of the millennium (the London Eye, the Shard, the Sky Garden) are little more than glorified viewing platforms. Some might argue that we’ve simply forgotten how to build beautiful places, and that modern buildings are bland regardless of their purpose. But elevated points for tourists to take photos also seem to have taken precedence over the construction of aesthetically pleasing public infrastructure. Will we ever change course? Never say never, but it doesn’t look likely in the near future. Tourists are happy to visit somewhere offering a good photo opportunity, and those building these places make too much money - if not from admittance, which is sometimes free as a planning condition, from the gift shops and pricey restaurants and bars that are never too far away. Trends are hard to reverse, but there are personal antidotes. Travel is more rewarding when you embark on a trip with curiosity, rather than a checklist. Ask questions, linger longer, read the plaques, and treat your destination as somebody’s home - not a product. You’ll be infinitely more likely to pick up on the details that make the whole endeavour worthwhile.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/tourism_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/tourism_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Staying productive when everything feels urgent</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2025/05/02/time-blocking-productivity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Staying productive when everything feels urgent" /><published>2025-05-02T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-05-02T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2025/05/02/time-blocking-productivity</id><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><summary type="html">We’ve all been there. One day you’re in control, the next you’re racing from meeting to meeting, unable to focus long enough to move anything forward in any meaningful way - unless, that is, you start protecting your time. When everything feels urgent and your calendar is under siege, the key to making progress lies in consciously carving out space for what matters most. A snowballing workload Years ago, I was a pure practitioner. I had a manageable amount of work and a nice clear schedule to complete it in. If the volume of tasks exceeded the number of hours in the day, I could simply inform my manager and they’d resolve the equation, either with more people or a streamlined backlog. But progress far enough in any career and that won’t last long. My expanded workload now consists not only of the doing itself, but also of strategising, planning, administrating, and managing - and with those responsibilities come all the related meetings, leaving my calendar much more crowded. This conundrum isn’t reserved for management types alone. As the Wall Street Journal recently reported, technology roles are becoming more demanding across the board. Companies are trying to do more with less, retracting perks and burdening workers with responsibilities that were previously spread across multiple roles, all in the name of “agility”. That out-of-control feeling is triggered by the absence of agency. You're on the hook for the work, but lack the authority to do anything There are few feelings worse than when the scales tip and your inbox is suddenly filling up more quickly than you can empty it. That out-of-control feeling is triggered by a perceived - and possibly real - absence of agency. You don’t have enough time to do everything you’re on the hook for, but you lack the authority to turn down work or bring in additional people to help. Even considering what to focus on first only burns more time. If your normal working hours are not enough to get everything done, it may be tempting to stay late to bring your to-do list under control - but will that actually help in the long run, or will it only mean you’re less productive tomorrow due to the resulting fatigue? It can feel like an insurmountable challenge. Working within constraints A typical recommendation to get ahead of this chaos is to take the time to note down your most important tasks for the day. Entrepreneur and venture capitalist Marc Andreessen, for example, is often cited for his approach of scribbling his three to five most pressing tasks on an index card just before he goes to bed, ready to begin the next day on the front foot. The thinking here makes obvious sense. Your time is finite and in a modern business environment there is always a lot going on. Therefore it is optimal to focus on a small number of actions that will make the most impact, and recording these in advance will help you to avoid trivial distractions. However, there are obvious issues with this approach if you’re not a self-employed founder or a C-level leader with full control over your calendar: It’s likely that you’ll receive urgent tasks from your manager or your customers, and not checking your emails until midday because you were engaging in focused work probably isn’t going to cut it. As a low- or mid-level employee, your time is not seen as sacred. People will see spare slots in your calendar and fill them, leaving you with no time to get on with the things on your high-priority list. Therefore while you might start the day with the best intentions, it’s very easy for things to descend into the kind of firefighting you sought to avoid. The solution: Prioritisation + time blocking Over time, I have settled on a straightforward approach that minimises the risk of that happening. The following tactic has emerged naturally for me over years - partly as a product of my inclination towards organisation, but also as a custom hybrid of various productivity systems out there online. I bolster the prioritisation system touted by gurus like Andreessen with time blocking. This means I not only identify the day’s most important tasks, but I also protect the time needed to get my head down and complete them. Together, task prioritisation and time blocking make high workloads more manageable At the beginning of each day, I review my calendar. Inevitably, some of my time is already reserved for meetings. Those were subject to filtering prior to accepting the invites1, and generally stay where they are. Then I turn to my to-do list. Working in order of priority, I estimate how long each task is likely to take and block out time on my calendar, as close to the start of the day as possible. I bundle small tasks (e.g. email replies) into a single block to avoid overcomplicating things and wasting time. I am careful not to book back-to-back tasks through the entire duration of the day. A spare 30-minute block here and there provides the opportunity to catch up on overrunning tasks and deal with any interruptions, new urgent requests, or personal emergencies that crop up. A ring-fenced lunch break is also non-negotiable - nobody can work for eight or more hours straight.2 Benefits of the hybrid system It’s a simple system - anything more intricate would risk consuming more of my time than it saved - but blocking out time in this way has a surprising number of direct and indirect benefits to my focus and productivity: I have time to do the things that matter. With my calendar already booked, it is unlikely that anyone will push additional meeting invites, meaning a greater overall productivity-to-meeting ratio. My IM status is automatically set to Busy. People are less likely to interrupt my focused work if that little circle is red rather than green. The cognitive load of selecting tasks is removed. There is a cognitive penalty to task switching, and time blocking not only allows me to focus on a single task for a set period, but also removes the need to consider what to do next. The next block arrives, and the next task is there ready to go, making it easier to maintain momentum.3 When interruptions do occur, they impact low-priority work. By frontloading my day with the most important work, other urgent tasks that “must be completed by COP” can be handled by pushing low-priority blocks further out. The big stuff still gets done. The prioritisation element ensures high-impact work is at the top of the pile, while time blocking ensures my colleagues - and my brain - know I’m focused on something and should only be interrupted for urgent matters. Together, they’re effective in restoring productivity and taking back control of my day. Your calendar is a reflection of your priorities. Make it intentional. Notes and references Never be afraid to decline a meeting invite if you think all the necessary information could be provided in a quick email. I’ve found a good tactic is to set my lunch block to 45 minutes. This defends my lunch time, ensuring I always have time to rest and eat. But also, because nobody books 15-minute meetings, it buys me some time to catch up on my inbox before the next block. I’m acutely aware that turning complex knowledge work into something akin to a factory assembly line could also be viewed as a criticism of this approach. It won’t be for everyone.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/productivity-time-blocking_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/productivity-time-blocking_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Humanising AI encourages intellectual lethargy</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2025/04/21/chatgpt-ai-anthropomorphism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Humanising AI encourages intellectual lethargy" /><published>2025-04-21T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-04-21T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2025/04/21/chatgpt-ai-anthropomorphism</id><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><summary type="html">I recently stumbled upon a Hacker News thread around a series of X posts about ChatGPT’s o3 model. Researchers noted that it “frequently fabricates actions it never took, and then elaborately justifies those actions when confronted”, in one case claiming to have received an incorrect result by running code on a laptop that it couldn’t possibly have had access to. “These behaviours are surprising,” Transluce wrote later in their thread. “It seems that despite being incredibly powerful at solving math and coding tasks, o3 is not by default truthful about its capabilities.” Yes, I did use AI to generate this image They theorised that these discrepencies are caused by the way ChatGPT handles conversations with multiple prompts and replies. Because the model cannot see the reasoning behind each previous response, it can only base future responses on the content of past replies. Lacking the context to know how they were generated, it sometimes makes up stories to fill the blanks. While this has interesting technical implications, some of the most interesting discussion on Hacker News was around the use of moral terms like “truthful” in relation to an AI model. One user, latexr, replied: “It is only surprising to those who refuse to understand how [large language models] work and continue to anthropomorphise them. There is no being ‘truthful’ here, the model has no concept of right or wrong, true or false. It’s not ‘lying’ to you, it’s spitting out text. It just so happens that sometimes that non-deterministic text aligns with reality, but you don’t really know when and neither does the model.” Your new best friend That person is correct, but the underlying issue is that technology companies increasingly try to hide that their products are simply complex systems, incapable of conscious thought. It’s not only ChatGPT that lacks knowledge of how its responses are generated - the user doesn’t see its workings either. Replies are wrapped in a layer of flowery, friendly language. In extreme cases, this leads to Her-esque stories of people falling in love with AI personas. But even for the regular user, it implies human-style reasoning and sets an expectation that the content of responses is more reliable than it really is. The royal weThere is precedent for attempting to convince users a soulless software product is a helpful assistant. From about 2017, between Windows 10 and 11, Microsoft implemented a tone shift that involved a jarring change of perspective. What were straightforward, efficient messages (&quot;Windows has encountered an error&quot;) suddenly became overly friendly (&quot;We're getting things ready for you&quot;, &quot;We need to restart&quot;). In that case it felt rather manipulative, as if Microsoft thought I might be more acceptant of its products' shortcomings if I felt like we were working as a team to tackle them. Intellectual lethargy Google search results have generally become less useful over the last decade, but the difference is that users expect they’ll need to apply their own logic and filters to whatever comes back. Scanning a page of results triggers an automatic mental assessment of each site’s reliability, and the answer to the user’s query is often an amalgamation of content from several links. Through a combination of hype and framing, AI models set a very different expectation. ChatGPT is positioned as the user’s trusted assistant, and it is therefore a fair assumption that it has already done the legwork to evaluate the information presented by each source and return the ultimate truth. Users expect they'll need to apply their own logic and filters to Google search results, but ChatGPT uses a tone that implies human-style reasoning This mostly holds true, but unburdened by the task of evaluating results themselves, the user is no longer in a critical state of mind. The combination of a single answer, the model’s human-like tone, and its confident rebuttal of challenges even when it’s in the wrong makes detecting errors - or as they’ve come to be known in online tech circles, “hallucinations” - not only a more challenging task, but one that is probably not front-of-mind for most users. In casual use cases that’s mostly a nuisance. But where AI is used in more professional applications, integrated within more complex systems, or used as part of efforts to control online narratives through censorship of results, the removal of any expectation of mental engagement on the part of the user becomes more of a problem - and one that will only increase in prevalence as LLM user bases grow and more people come to trust their chirpy tone.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/ai-humanisation_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/ai-humanisation_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Finding comfort in the green hills outside my window</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2025/04/16/green-hills-outside-my-window" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finding comfort in the green hills outside my window" /><published>2025-04-16T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-04-16T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2025/04/16/hills-outside-my-window</id><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><summary type="html">As I mentioned in a recent post, I moved to a new home a few months ago. My new place sits atop a hill, and the window to the right of my desk happens to look away from the city, over the tops of the houses opposite and off into the green hills beyond. I can see all the way to the trees on the horizon. It’s a shame that I can’t post a photo without the risk of doxxing myself. I wouldn’t say it’s especially picturesque. You wouldn’t put it on a postcard - the electricity pylons and roads are a firm reminder that this is not, in fact, the countryside. But those rolling - albeit cluttered - hills are still a welcome contrast to the density of the City and the grime of the local high street. ChatGPT's approximation of my view, with exaggerated greenery - Ghiblified, naturally I feel as though that view keeps me in touch with nature, if only by a strand. On frosty mornings, the greenery takes on a pale hue. When the rainclouds roll in, the hills disappear behind a sheet of grey mist. On sunny days, I can see the shadows cast by the clouds drifting across the landscape. And in the bright spring evenings, my wife and I watch some fantastic sunsets disappear over the horizon, bathing our living room in golden light on the way. Until I moved, I didn’t realise how much I was missing without this light and airiness. For seven years, I lived in a studio flat that faced west. My view was of the wall of the building opposite. In the winter, the sun often didn’t reach my window at all, setting before it moved far enough around in the sky. And even in the summer, it was partially obstructed by the tree cover outside. If all you can see is man-made structures, then it feels impossible to look past man-made problems. If all you can see is man-made structures, then it feels impossible to look past man-made problems. My distant view of the landscape is a reminder of the true constants - the hills, the weather - that continue to exist no matter what we build on top. For thousands of years, people have observed them in the same way. That’s a calming thought in the face of day-to-day stresses. When I bought the place, the view barely factored into my decision - it was just a nice bonus. But after living here for a while, I think green sightlines have become a greater consideration if I ever decide to move again. It’s almost as though humans weren’t built to stare at grey tarmac every day.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/green-hills_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/green-hills_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Fixing weak WiFi and slow speeds on my home network</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2025/04/08/home-network-weak-wifi-slow-speeds" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fixing weak WiFi and slow speeds on my home network" /><published>2025-04-08T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-04-08T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2025/04/08/home-networking-weak-wifi-slow-speeds</id><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><summary type="html">I moved to a new home late last year, and immediately faced a whole range of connectivity issues. For a techie like myself, reliant on a functional network both for work and for fun, that was a big problem. So I implemented a few different solutions to find a fix (some of which were arguably overkill). It all started when I realised that my previous fibre broadband provider didn’t offer service to my new building. After searching for a replacement, the best option seemed to be Virgin Media. I signed up for their 500Mbps package, plugged in the router they provided, and thought I was set. How wrong I was. Even from my early visits to my new flat, camping out on the floor of the empty bedroom and waiting for Ikea deliveries, it was clear something was wrong. My phone stumbled along at 20Mbps, and frequently disconnected from the WiFi altogether. Streaming a football match or a Formula 1 race to entertain myself during those long waits was impossible. I initially put it down to teething issues. I had just activated the connection, and I assumed it was midway through some kind of adjustment process, after which it would reach optimal speeds. But days turned into weeks, weeks into months, and I decided I needed to dig into what was going on. Diagnosing the issue Through a combination of observation, research, trial, and error, I worked out that there were two main reasons behind the poor network performance. First was that my new building was simply very noisy. A quick glance at a NetSpot report revealed tens of networks in the near vicinity, spread across all available channels. While not the end of the world, this meant that sometimes my WiFi signal was probably simply being drowned out. My second discovery was that the Virgin Media Hub 3 is notoriously bad. It has been around for six years at the time of writing, and the internet is full of complaints from people in exactly my situation who expected a decent WiFi signal but had nothing but trouble with speeds and reliability. Unfortunately, if its full signal strength couldn’t shout over the noise, it wasn’t ever going to be enough on its own. The cable outlet was located in my living room, so it would be a lot of effort to move the Hub to a more central location, and even if I did, there was no guarantee it would work. Fix #1: Ethernet connections Armed with the knowledge that my WiFi problems were probably unfixable, but with no time or backup kit, I implemented the easiest possible fix: connecting as many devices as possible directly to the router. This was a simple process for my PlayStation 5 - I just ran an ethernet cable around the living room skirting board. Reaching my home office took slightly more effort, as I needed to detach and reattach the connector to poke the cable through a hole in the wall to reach the router on the other side. Hooking the devices up directly gave me a first glimpse of the internet speeds I was paying for, with downloads consistently exceeding 500Mbps. However, this did nothing to solve my problems with mobile devices. In the bedroom, my iPhone still jumped between WiFi and 5G at random. More problematically, despite sitting only a metre or so from the Hub, my work laptop sometimes dropped out in the middle of Teams calls. Fix #2: Replacement router It was clear the Hub 3’s WiFi wasn’t up to scratch, so I bought the best router I could find in stock in my local area - an Asus TUF-AX3000 V2. This isn’t a router review, but I was pleasantly surprised. Besides looking like a cross between a brutalist building and an alien spacecraft, the TUF-AX3000 was very easy to set up - connecting almost immediately after I switched my Hub to modem-only mode - and boasts a flashy mobile app for network monitoring and management, with security backed by Trend Micro. The Asus TUF-AX3000 V2 router has a distinctly &quot;gamer&quot; look Most importantly, it uses WiFi 6, and instantly boosted my signal strength. From the moment I switched to the new router, my Teams calls worked flawlessly and connections seemed much more stable in general. It wasn’t perfect - connections could still drop sometimes in remote corners - but I found an easy solution, buying a longer ethernet cable and a power extension cord so I could position the router on top of a cabinet, away from any obstructions. Since then, the signal has been perfect everywhere. Fix #3: Ethernet switch With more reliable WiFi, I could have stopped there. But I wanted the best possible connection from my laptops, and that meant giving them a wired connection to the router when working at my desk. With only the one cable available in my office, I bought a little switch to allow multiple connections. I was expecting another chunky outlay, but I picked up a TP-Link TL-SG105 for about £15, making it one of the cheaper components in my setup. It’s a simple device - plug and play with no management interface - but I like how compact and sturdy it is, like a mini version of an enterprise rack switch. The TP-Link TL-SG105 switch is basic, but it's a neat little package The switch lets me connect multiple devices to the network via ethernet, meaning I can wire in both my desktop PC and the Microsoft Surface dock that provides power, networking, and USB ports to my laptops via a single connector. It was a fair bit of work, but the extra additions to my setup mean I’m now sorted with reliable 500Mbps+ speeds across all my devices. End result and next steps The new router and switch mean that my network, originally a standard hub-and-spoke model centred around the Virgin Media Hub, now looks a little more complex. Of course, that additional complexity also brings two new devices to power, maintain, and eventually replace, but it has drastically improved my experience without too much capital or overhead cost. My home network needed a small upgrade to work reliably across multiple rooms What’s next? Well, there are a whole load of projects I’d love to tackle now I’m more settled in one spot. Tinkering with an open-source smart home sounds like an attractive option, but even just being able to set up a Raspberry Pi project in a permanent position brings a lot of potential. But first, I need to take care of more practical matters - before I can even think about an IoT themostat, my new home needs a fresh coat of paint.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/home-networking_0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/home-networking_0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Endpoint detection and response (EDR) - setting the record straight</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2024/07/20/crowdstrike-bug-edr-setting-record-straight" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Endpoint detection and response (EDR) - setting the record straight" /><published>2024-07-20T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-07-20T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2024/07/20/crowdstrike-bug-edr-setting-record-straight</id><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><summary type="html">When I went to bed on the evening of Friday 19th July, I couldn’t sleep. It was a stuffy summer’s night in London, and the adrenaline was still pumping through my veins after one of the more notable days in recent memory for cyber security. Still, laying awake gave me time to reflect on what I’d seen.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/mcas.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/mcas.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Centralisation, repeatability, and automation in a modular SOC</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2023/11/26/modular-soc-centralisation-repeatability-automation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Centralisation, repeatability, and automation in a modular SOC" /><published>2023-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2023/11/26/modular-soc-centralisation-repeatability-automation</id><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><summary type="html">The dictionary definition of “modular” leaves a little to be desired: “Employing or involving a module or modules as the basis of design or construction.” What is implied, but that I would make explicit, is that parts of the whole can be swapped out easily while maintaining the functionality of the product.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/mcas.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/mcas.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cyber security sometimes means learning things backwards</title><link href="https://mattcasmith.net/2023/03/26/cyber-security-learning-things-backwards" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cyber security sometimes means learning things backwards" /><published>2023-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mattcasmith.net/2023/03/26/cyber-security-learning-things-backwards</id><author><name>mattcasmith</name></author><summary type="html">Stick around cyber security Twitter or LinkedIn for long enough and you’ll likely see somebody raise a question about how to get into the industry. You’ll also likely see a reply that describes a kind of rite of passage from sysadmin, to SOC analyst, to just about any other security role.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/mcas.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mattcasmith.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/mcas.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>